<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A missive to His Majesty of Great Britain, King James written divers yeers since by Doctor Carier ; conteining [sic] the motives of his conversion to Catholike religion ; vvith a notable fore-sight of the present distempers both in the church and state of His Majesties dominions, and his advice for the prevention thereof.</title>
            <author>Carier, Benjamin, 1566-1614.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 164 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 48 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A34212</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C572</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8830</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13108468</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13108468</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97574</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A34212)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97574)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 410:7)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A missive to His Majesty of Great Britain, King James written divers yeers since by Doctor Carier ; conteining [sic] the motives of his conversion to Catholike religion ; vvith a notable fore-sight of the present distempers both in the church and state of His Majesties dominions, and his advice for the prevention thereof.</title>
                  <author>Carier, Benjamin, 1566-1614.</author>
                  <author>Strange, N., 17th cent.</author>
                  <author>James I, King of England, 1566-1625.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 28, [10], 54 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[Paris :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"To the reader" signed: N. Strange.</note>
                  <note>Imprint reads: First printed at Liege, and novv re-printed at Paris, vvith some marginall notes, and a previous discourse to the like purpose.</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>Marginal notes.</note>
                  <note>"The names of some who have lately been ministers or university men in England and Scotland, and are now converted to the Catholike faith": p. [1]-[4].</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Catholic converts --  England.</term>
               <term>Church and state --  England.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-10</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97574:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> A MISSIVE TO His Majeſty of <hi>Great Britain,</hi> KING JAMES.</p>
                  <p>Written divers yeers ſince, By Doctor CARIER.</p>
                  <p>Conteining the Motives of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to <hi>Catholike Religion.</hi> VVith a notable fore-ſight of the preſent diſtempers both in the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> of <hi>His Majeſties</hi> Dominions: And his Advice for the prevention thereof.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Eructavit cor meum verbum bonum; dico ego opera mea Regi.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <bibl> Pſal. 44.</bibl>
                  </q>
                  <p>Firſt printed at LIEGE, and novv re-printed at PARIS: VVith ſome Marginall Notes; And a previous Diſcourſe to the like purpoſe. M. DC. XLIX.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97574:2"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97574:2"/>
                  <head>To the Reader of what Reformation ſoever in mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters of Religion.</head>
                  <p>LIghting caſually of late on the enſuing <hi>Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> written above thirty yeares ago by one of the moſt learned of his time among Engliſh Divines, <hi>Doctor Carier,</hi> Chaplain to King <hi>James,</hi> and ſent to His Majeſty, by him, as a juſtification of his then deſerting the <hi>Proteſtant Cauſe,</hi> and conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> as a ſubmiſſive teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony of his loyalty to his Soveraigne; and as a faithfull Servants advice to his royall Maſter, for his future ſafety both in this and the world to come; I could not but ſigh with a groaning <hi>Utinam,</hi> that the King had entertained his ſuggeſtion with a more yeelding regard. Had he been ſo happy, I dare boldly pronounce the temporall State of his left Kingdome, (to ſay nothing of the other world) and poſterity, had not been ſo deplorable, as now with mournfull countenances we are forced to behold it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Dr. Carier</hi> (being a man born and bred from his infancy in the <hi>Proteſtant Profeſſion,</hi> orderly promo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his academicall degree, and above others in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deared to his Prince for his greater proficiency in the literature and principles of the <hi>Engliſh Church,</hi> .i. in the grounds of <hi>Luther</hi> or <hi>Calvin,</hi> or both, with others of the late Reformers of the old Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian world) fore-ſaw to what tragicall concluſions their premiſes did diſpoſe, and what Cockatrices
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97574:3"/> would be conuaturally hatch'd out of their eggs, when time ſerved to ſit long upon them: he fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaw they would certainely prove destructive to Church and State, where ever they found good ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance. Nor can I ſay the <hi>Doctor</hi> was a Prophet by that fore-ſight, more then he, who ſeeing the heavens over-caſt with clouds, prognoſticates a tempeſt; or he who ſeeing Gunpowder enough laid under the corner ſtones of a building, and the match fired, fore-tells a quick ſubverſion of that Fabrick. A man becomes not a Prophet by ſuch a prediction, but contrarily he is to be eſteemed ſhort-ſighted, and of little conſideration, that ſees not thoſe neceſſary effects, if he ſees the cauſe.</p>
                  <p>Take firſt for example ſake, thoſe Doctrines of your firſt <hi>Generall</hi> in the late Reformation, <hi>Luther</hi> in his Comments upon <hi>S. Paul</hi> to the <hi>Galat.</hi> in his bookes <hi>de libertate Chriſtiana,</hi> and <hi>de ſeculari po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtate, That Chriſtians are not tied to the obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vance of the Decalogue, but freed by faith from all Laws. That among Chriſtians there muſt be no Superiority. That there is no hope of ſalvation or ſafety, as long as the Common-wealth is governed by humane or civill Lawes. That God is to be prayed unto, that Magiſtrates be not obeyed by their Subjects.</hi> Theſe Doctrines are impugned and execrated by all <hi>Catholikes,</hi> as their Books do every where teſtifie: but take them, I ſay, and digeſt them once for truths, and then tell me what ſequeles will naturally follow, or rather what will not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low? tell me, if you can, to what end Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>call or Civill Lawes are enacted? what obedience can Princes or Magiſtrates of either ſort expect from thoſe they count their Subjects? who ſcoure in his owne poſſeſſions? what curb for vice? To
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97574:3"/> thoſe points of reforming Doctrine, add his ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſawcy cenſure of temporall Princes in the cited book <hi>de Seculari Poteſt. Scire debetis quod ab initio Mundi rara admodum avis eſt princeps prudens; ad huc multò rarior Princeps probus: ſunt commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niter maximè fatui; ac peſſimi nebulones ſuper ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ram, ſunt Lictores &amp; Carnifices Dei. It is a thing that all ought to take notice of, that from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the world a prudent Prince hath been a very rare bird, and much rarer a Prince morally honeſt: they are moſt commonly the verieſt fools and grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt knaves on earth, they are the Catchpoles and Hangmen of God.</hi> Whether this proceeding as Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine from the mouth and pen of one reputed a <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Saint,</hi> be not apt to breed diſreſpect of Princes in their Subjects, and to ſtir theſe to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, contempt, and rebellion againſt them, I appeale to others judgement?</p>
                  <p>Adde again his ſpirited incouragements againſt <hi>Biſhops</hi> in his <hi>Bulla contra ordinem Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cum. Quicunque opem ferunt</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>corpus, bona &amp; famam in hoc impendunt, ut Epiſcopatus Devaſtentur, &amp;c.</hi> And again, <hi>Evangelium quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cunque venit, oportet ut tumultuetur; niſi id fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciat, non eſt verum. Whoſoever afford their aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, and imploy their ſtrength; goods, and cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit to waſt and deſtroy Biſhopricks, and to root out Epiſcopall Government, they are the beloved chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God, and true Chriſtians, obedient to God, and reſiſting the Ordinances of the Devill: and on the contrary ſide, whoſoever maintaine E-Epiſcopall Government, and obey it, they are the Miniſters of Satan: whereſoever the Goſpell comes it muſt breed tumults, unleſſe it do ſo, it is a ſigne it is not the right or true.</hi> More might be added
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97574:4"/> out of his booke <hi>Contra Regem Angliae,</hi> of his in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſulting foule language againſt Princes, Church, and Biſhops; but what I have already produced is ſufficient to demonſtrate, that one converſant in his Schoole muſt quickly diſcover him altogether deſtructive of all order in Church and State. But before I go any further, I cannot but wonder, that the pretended Biſhops in England did not ſee them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves Mar-Prelates, I mean deſtroyers of their owne Government, (put Deane and Chapter to boot) and conſequently of their Church, whileſt they ſided ſo ſtrongly with <hi>Luther,</hi> and magnified his reformation; which to do, was <hi>co ipſo,</hi> as you may read in his words, utterly to aboliſh <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> and to cut their owne throats. <hi>O inſenſari<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> O ſenſleſſe and unwiſe men! what bewitcht you in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſo blind a ſtupidity, as not to ſee ſo palpable an error and contradiction in your practiſe?</p>
                  <p>Secondly, take this Dogmaticall point of your other grand Reformer <hi>Calvin</hi> (all <hi>Catholikes</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime againſt it, as moſt execrable blaſphemy) tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched by D. <hi>Carier</hi> in his Letter, <hi>That God pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinates to evill; That he is the Author, willer, and promoter of what men call evill, as well as of thoſe they call good actions,</hi> and then tell me what ratio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall check you can find againſt any crime, how enor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous ſoever? be it treaſon or rebellion, againſt Church or Prince, with the ſlaughter of both; be it blaſphemy againſt God, or Deicide it ſelf, as far as humane malice can reach towards it; hath not the perpetrator a ready protection to juſtifie his fact? <hi>God predeſtinated him unto it, God would have it ſo, who muſt not obey God? or who may law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully reſiſt his decrees?</hi> tell me again, what Church, or Prince, or private perſon can promiſe himſelfe ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97574:4"/> whilſt every villaine hath that principle to juſtifie his attempt againſt them?</p>
                  <p>Theſe and the like Doctrines, diſperſed up and downe in the written works of the late <hi>Reformers,</hi> obvious to be met withall both in the Authors them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and in others that write of them, did <hi>D. Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rier</hi> ponder, and in them ſaw cleerly the effects, that by an unavoidable connexion (as long as the cauſes were kept in their vigour) were to flow out of them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and theſe were the overthrow of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State.</hi> Nor did he ſee theſe effects only in their cauſe, but really extant in themſelves, he ſaw the <hi>Germans,</hi> till then commended for loyall to their Princes, and obedient to their ſpirituall Paſtors, preſently upon <hi>Luthers</hi> firing and blowing the coales with a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence of Reformation, divided among themſelves in open Rebellion againſt their Liege Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> 5. without regard to Eccleſiaſticall Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours. He ſaw their Churches waſted and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaned, and mens manners in a moment altered in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to worſe, he ſaw the <hi>Genevean</hi> tumults againſt their true <hi>Prince</hi> and <hi>Biſhop,</hi> their <hi>Reformer Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vin</hi> (that ſo he might be more abſolutely indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent of all, and chiefe over all) being the Incen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diary. Nor can I thinke him ignorant of the Councell held at <hi>Geneva,</hi> in the yeer 1560. for the murdering of the <hi>King and Queen of France,</hi> the Queen Mother with the royall iſſue, the Catholike Peers &amp; Magiſtrates of the Kingdom, the two great Reformers <hi>Calvin</hi> and <hi>Beza</hi> being Authors and principalls in the Conſpiracy, as <hi>Bolſecus</hi> in the life of <hi>Calvin</hi> makes appeare out of a Letter of the ſaid <hi>Calvin</hi> to his trusty friend <hi>Viretus;</hi> he ſaw the ruinous devaſtations that fell upon the flouriſhing Kingdome of <hi>France</hi> from the ſame fiery ſpirit of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97574:5"/> 
                     <hi>Reformation,</hi> which <hi>Herod-like</hi> was most malici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous againſt the venerable Antiquities of the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. He ſaw again (to omit others) the rebellion of the <hi>Scots</hi> againſt their Soveraigne <hi>Queen Mary,</hi> our preſent Kings Grandmother, who afterwards by the arm and axe of the old cauſe, was beheaded at <hi>Fodringham Caſtle</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> the common Hang-man of <hi>London</hi> by publike authority (O eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall ſhame to the Engliſh and Scottiſh Nation!) imbruing his hands in her royall blood. And ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving how hand in hand reall deſtruction, rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lion with their iſſue out-rages, and their ſiſter pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ence of <hi>Reformation</hi> traverſed other Countreyes; he ſaw that one could not ſtand long parted from the other throughout <hi>King James</hi> his Dominions, ſo gave him a ſeaſonable warning of it; and as a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vident <hi>Noe</hi> ſhewed his Majeſty a ſafe Arke to pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent the Deluge, if he pleaſed. But to the preſent woe of his poſterity, and their loyall Subjects, through ill private choice, or counſell from others, he neglected the wholeſome advice of his knowing and faithfull ſervant the <hi>Doctor.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now though the publiſhing of this <hi>Epiſtolar Treatiſe</hi> comes too late for the effect firſt intended to <hi>King James,</hi> yet ſeeing the old principles ſtill ſtanding, and the authority of their founders ſtill maintained by the Reformed Church of <hi>England:</hi> And againe, ſeeing our Kingdome in blood from Sea to Sea, with wounds inflicted, doubled, and redoubled by them, (though few reflecting whence the blowes do originally proceed) I thought it no ill office of a Patriot (though now in a kind of ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ile) to endeavour a ſtop to my Countreyes evills; as far forth as the reading of a ſheet or two of printed paper might contribute thereunto, by preſenting all
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97574:5"/> whom it may concern (and whom doth it not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern,) with a freſh view of <hi>D. Cariers</hi> advice. The old proverb (out of the Prophet <hi>Iſay,</hi> cap. 28. v. 19.) is, <hi>Vexatio dat intellectum, vexation gives underſtanding;</hi> it ſometimes cures mad men, and brings them to themſelves againe. Perhaps the ſmart of ſo many blowes may make men reflect whence they have good and bad derived unto them, and render them more capable to regard the <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctors</hi> remedy, then whilſt they were blinded with fulneſſe, eaſe and proſperity; His remedie in a word is an obedient return of all unto that <hi>Church,</hi> whence thoſe <hi>Reformers</hi> rebelliouſly apoſtated; the charge of which Church is to execrate to the pit of hell the blaſphemies and ſeditious principles of <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> to reduce all to a ſound ſave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing beliefe, with a good conſcience, to order all in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their due poſtures of obedience to <hi>temporall</hi> and <hi>ſpirituall</hi> Superiours; and in a word, not to live prophanely, as men deſtitute of the knowledge of the true God; nor thirſting one anothers blood, nor invading one anothers rights, as Wolves and Tygers: but as the <hi>Apoſtle</hi> ſaith, <hi>(Tit. cap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 12.) <hi>ſobriè, &amp; juſtè, &amp; piè,</hi> ſoberly for our ſelves, juſtly towards our neighbour, and piouſly to God, or as the true patterne of all Juſtice <hi>Chriſt Jeſus</hi> hath taught us, <hi>reddentes quae ſunt Caeſaris, Caeſari, &amp; quae ſunt Dei, Deo:</hi> By this you have one reaſon why <hi>D. Cariers</hi> Letter is republiſhed.</p>
                  <p>Another reaſon is to ſhew the world that the late converſion of D. <hi>Tho. Vane,</hi> late Chaplaine to the Kings Majeſty that now is, and of Dean <hi>Creſſey</hi> (ſo much talked of in <hi>England;</hi> and the more by reaſon of their learned bookes printed to ſatiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie all why they became <hi>Roman Catholikes)</hi> and of
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97574:6"/> many other prime wits of our Univerſities (ſome whereof are hereafter particularly mentioned) who have lately trodden the ſame paths, utterly forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king thir former <hi>Tenets</hi> in Religion, not for tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>porall gain, (as all men know) unleſſe it be of po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verty and perſecution, is not a thing new, ſtrange, or to be wondred at.</p>
                  <p>When <hi>D. Carier</hi> liſted himſelf into the <hi>Militia</hi> of the <hi>Roman Church,</hi> (chooſing rather as <hi>Moſes</hi> did in <hi>Exodus</hi> to be afflicted with the true <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> then proſper among the <hi>Aegyptians;</hi> and to be, according to the <hi>Pſalmiſts</hi> Dialect, an abject in the Houſe of God, rather then inhabite the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of ſinners) there were many circumſtances that might make ſome inconſiderate people to won<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der at it.</p>
                  <p>The Church then called <hi>Proteſtant,</hi> whereof it ſeems he counted himſelfe a member, was at that time moſt flouriſhing in <hi>England;</hi> they had a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble ſupreme head of above forty yeares ſtanding without interruption, (after the title was firſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken by <hi>Henry the eight,</hi> to legitimate his Marriage with <hi>Anno Bolen,</hi> whileſt his firſt wife lived, it ceaſed during the reigne of his daughter <hi>Q. Mary,</hi> and ſo was interrupted) in whom by Oath they ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledged the ſupremest power in all things under heaven. They gloried in their <hi>Prelats</hi> &amp; <hi>Biſhops,</hi> not found in any reformed Churches out of their Kings Dominions, they had ſome colourable pretence to a ſucceſſion of Miniſteriall Ordinations, and Miſſions from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Chriſt.</hi> They thought they had their Church well and properly marked by thirty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>nine <hi>Articles.</hi> They boaſted of a <hi>Liturgie</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated with the blood of Martyrs, more com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleat for all uſes, and ſatisfactory to the people, thou
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97574:6"/> any of the neighbouring <hi>Reformations</hi> injoyed. They had differences of daies, ſome kept holy, o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers faſted. They uſed ſome ſolemnities in the ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration of their two <hi>Sacraments.</hi> They had decencies in their <hi>Burialls.</hi> They had ſeverall pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſes outwardly religious: and in brief, they had ſo many Reliques of the old Chriſtianity of their Countrey, as did manifeſtly distinguiſh them from <hi>Jews, Turks,</hi> and other more prophane people. All which as they were plauſible ſtayes to with-hold men in the <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and not to thinke on any other, eſpecially if they were born and bred in <hi>Proteſtancy:</hi> ſo made they any mans converſion to <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> in thoſe daies, more remark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able, more wondered at, and more ſubject to the queſtion, <hi>what moved him to forſake the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant?</hi> Withall <hi>D. Cariers</hi> favour with his Prince, together with his great learning, and good parts, making him capable of the chiefeſt ſpirituall dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities and promotions in the Kingdome, might well move many to take notice of his converſion, and wonder he ſhould change both his preſent poſſeſſions, &amp; pregnant hopes of more, for the poor contemptible being of an exiled <hi>Papiſt,</hi> perhaps ſcanted in ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſaries to live and breath.</p>
                  <p>But now to uſe the <hi>Prophet Jeremies</hi> words, in his Threnes <hi>(c.</hi> 4. <hi>v.</hi> 1. <hi>cap.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 2. though in a diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent ſenſe) <hi>Obſcuratum eſt aurum; mutatus eſt color optimus; diſperſi ſunt lapides Sanctuarii in capite omnium platearum:</hi> what ſeemed gold a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> is now altogether darkned, and caſt off as droſſe, the moſt ſpecious of their fair colours is faded, (an argument it was of no long laſting complexion) the ſeeming corner ſtones of their ſeeming Sanctuary are diſperſed in the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97574:7"/> head of all the ſtreets. The ſworne ſupreme head of their <hi>Church,</hi> though gray, aged, and well de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved of them, is made his vaſſalls ſubject, their ward, their captive, ſcarce allowed to keep his own head on his ſhoulders; and whilſt it is on, is lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle leſſe then baſely foot-balled by the miſcreants of his owne Subjects.</p>
                  <p>Their <hi>Biſhops</hi> once the corner-ſtones of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Sanctuary,</hi> or <hi>Reformation,</hi> are even levelled to the flock by their owne Diſciplinated ſheep: yea, I may ſay, <hi>facti ſunt opprobrium vicinis, ſubſanna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio &amp; illuſio his qui in circuitu ſunt: they are tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly become a reproach to their neighbours, a ſcorne and mock to all about them.</hi> The Reformation, now thought beſt for <hi>England,</hi> can ſubſiſt (they ſay) as well without <hi>Biſhops,</hi> as their neighbour Churches. Their old Ordination of Miniſters (and as old as it is, onely invented in King <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixths daies) is already laid to the wall, this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> hath found a newer way to ſupply the Biſhops Office; there is no pretence to Miſſion, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rived by any order from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> all claime an equall right to the Pulpit, <hi>Tinkers, Weavers, Taylors, Fidlers, Souldiers;</hi> nor do any faile of novell-hunting auditors, ſome of the old <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant Preachers</hi> ſilenced by the <hi>Parliament,</hi> others fallen to ſilence of themſelves, as not knowing what to preach to day, for fear they be driven to contradict it in the next Sermon, or to fight for their Pulpit; others preach according to the times<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though againſt their owne conſciences, to ſave their livings. And good God! what non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenſe, ignorances, ſeditious &amp; rebellious Doctrines, yea Blaſphemies, do the Tubs and Pulpits ring with, whilſt they are knocks and belaboured by
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97574:7"/> thoſe new Mountebank Predicants or Praters, who decry and contemn the <hi>Lords Prayer,</hi> the <hi>Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles Creed,</hi> and <hi>ten Commandements,</hi> as rags and reliques of Popery and Superſtition.</p>
                  <p>Their <hi>Liturgie</hi> (which began in the nonage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign of <hi>Edw. the</hi> 6. and after ſome years interrup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, got ſtronger footing by an Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> daies, and ſo was become almoſt of <hi>fourſcore years</hi> preſcription, half as old as one of our Grandfathers) is decryed, antiquated by the preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> contemned by the people, and ſucceeded by a new thing called a <hi>Directory,</hi> of 4. or 5. yeares unquiet ſtanding, which begins already to loſe credit with its firſt accepters, though as yet the ſtronger Faction (not without frequent ſcuffles and blood-ſhed) keeps it perforce in many Churches; and what is kept in perforce it neither likely to breed devotion, unleſſe it be of the new garb, nor to be of long durance, if the old Proverb faile not, <hi>Nihil violentum diuturnum.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Their former marke of thirty nine <hi>Articles</hi> is little regarded, if not quite out of date: yea, which is worſe, the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> the perpetuall marke or ſymbol of a Chriſtian, is queſtioned and hath ſtood theſe ſix or ſeven yeares ſubjected to the diſquiſition of the <hi>Parliaments</hi> ſubpedancan Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vines, without determination as yet, whether it be to be imbraced all and intirely for truth, or on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly part.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the ſolemnities of their <hi>Sacraments<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> I need not tell you into what omiſſion and confuſion they are fallen about their <hi>Lords Supper,</hi> ſome Churches having had no Communion at all theſe ſix or ſeven years: ſome uſing it after the old fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion, others after the new: ſome receive it knee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97574:8"/> ſome ſtanding, ſome ſitting, none of the new<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modell'd <hi>Miniſters</hi> (ſome of the old did, others de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rided it) claiming more power to conſecrate, then the Layicks of the <hi>Parliament</hi> can give them, which they know to be no more then the Bakers that ſell them bread can ſell with it.</p>
                  <p>As for their <hi>Sacrament</hi> of <hi>Baptiſme,</hi> beſides their novelty in the manner and circumſtances, it is certaine they are defective in ſome places, even in the eſſentialls, I meane in the words of <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution,</hi> and application of water, ſome ſaying (in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtead of <hi>I baptize thee in the Name of the Father, &amp;c.) We take thee into the Congregation of the faithfull.</hi> Whether all apply the water either at all, or rightly, is more then my diſtance out of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey permits me to learne, but not more then I have reaſon to doubt of: And where any of the eſſentialls are wanting, there certainely the child is not baptized, but left as he was borne, a child of perdition by the ſtate of originall ſin.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Burialls</hi> now among the Reformed in <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> are in a manner prophane, in many places the dead being throwne into the ground like dogs, and not a word ſaid; nor have they willingly more dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferences of daies, by holy or faſt, in memory of Chriſtian myſteries, then Turks and Infidells: nor finally is there any thing almoſt out of the <hi>Catholikes</hi> hands left in the Countrey that can per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade a travelling ſtranger to think <hi>England</hi> to be rather Chriſtian then Turkiſh, excepting the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward ſhape of <hi>Churches,</hi> which of the charges to alter them be not a <hi>Remora,</hi> may be alſo reformed ere long.</p>
                  <p>To theſe <hi>metamorphoſies</hi> or changes of late in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions into the preſent of a little freſher coine,
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97574:8"/> adde the confounded Chaos we ſee now in matters of Religion throughout the Kingdome, God Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty permitting the monſter of <hi>Reformation</hi> to reveale its owne turpitude, and to betray its ſelfe by its cloven feet of Sects and Diviſions, to be what indeed it is, that men might more eaſily diſcern it, to beat it down and detest it.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Luther</hi> himſelfe at the firſt, and afterwards his followers of whatſoever <hi>Reformation,</hi> were mightily tormented with thoſe queſtions of the <hi>Catholikes, Where the Church afterwards called the Lutheran, or Reformed, was in the yeare of Chriſt,</hi> 1512.? (when <hi>Luther</hi> was an <hi>Auguſtine Frier</hi> in his Monaſtery, a <hi>Catholike</hi> in communion with the <hi>Pope of Rome) Who was then a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant? In what Countrey did he live? What was his name?</hi> the queſtion is not, <hi>Who was then a Proteſtant in name?</hi> without asking them, we know by Hiſtories, that the <hi>Lutherans</hi> had the name of <hi>Proteſtants</hi> ſome yeares after the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation begun, from their <hi>Covenants</hi> and <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtations</hi> firſt made at <hi>Spire,</hi> and afterwards at <hi>Smalcald</hi> in <hi>Germany,</hi> when finding their party growing ſtrong, they began to take head againſt their <hi>Catholike</hi> Soveraigne <hi>Charles the fifth.</hi> Nor was the queſtion, who was then (before <hi>Luthers</hi> forſaking his cloiſtre and former Religion) oppoſite to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or of a different beliefe from hers? This queſtion had been eaſily anſwered by naming the <hi>Huſſits, Wickleſians, Berengarians, Arrians,</hi> and others, which for particular points of Doctrine, were as different from <hi>Luther,</hi> as he from the <hi>Catholike;</hi> but the meaning of the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion was, and ſtill is, Who did then believe all thoſe points of Faith, and onely thoſe, which
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97574:9"/> 
                     <hi>Luther,</hi> or any other <hi>after-Reformer</hi> did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards believe, and wherein they differed from the beliefe of <hi>Catholikes,</hi> which they pretended to reforme? this hath been from the beginning, and ſtill is a tormenting question to all of the <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches,</hi> and though daily asked by <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> Writers, and Diſcourſers, yet to this day could never be anſwered, with any ſatisfaction or proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility worthy a Schollers pen.</p>
                  <p>If now in this <hi>November,</hi> 1648. I ſhould aske who is a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> in <hi>England?</hi> .i. one holding all thoſe points of faith, and only thoſe (what o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther definition of a <hi>Proteſtant</hi> to give I know not, but deſire the learned <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to agree in it, and to ſet it downe, that he, who deſires to be one of their number, may know what he deſires,) which <hi>Luther</hi> the ſuppoſed Grandfather of <hi>Proteſtancy,</hi> and Enemy to <hi>Catholikes,</hi> profeſſed to believe? perhaps it would prove as troubleſome, or unſatisfia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble a <hi>Quaere</hi> as the former: yea, if I ſhould aske what three or four Schollers (ſpeaking of thoſe that are come to ſome eminency in learning, and to have ſome conceit of themſelves for it) are to be found in the Kingdome juſtly agreeing in all matters of faith? yea, to come cloſer to the purpoſe, if the queſtion were, what one man (ſetting the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> aſide). is there to be found of the ſame opinion now in matters of ſaith, that he was of, on the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of <hi>November,</hi> 1640? (the day before the preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> began) perhaps it would put you to a long ſearch, before you met a ſure ſatisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctory anſwer.</p>
                  <p>Lest you ſhould think I speake too much at ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, conſider I beſeech you, how frequently you meet with men, ſeriouſly and deliberately ſaying,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97574:9"/> 
                     <hi>Pox on it, rather then hazard my life, liberty, or fortunes, I'le be of any profeſſion. I'le keep my conſcience to my ſelf, but I'le never loſe my land for want of outward compliance, or conformity with the prevailing Multitude.</hi> And really their practice both in Religion and Loyalty is ſquared by that <hi>Dictamen;</hi> Of what <hi>Religion</hi> I pray you do you count theſe? Are they <hi>Proteſtants?</hi> Weighing them in the true ſcale of the <hi>Sanctuary,</hi> I take them to be <hi>Nulliſidians,</hi> indifferent, for <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity,</hi> or the <hi>Turkiſh Turbant,</hi> in evident ſtate of damnation for their ſoules; and that <hi>Tyre</hi> and <hi>Sidon</hi> may eſcape with a more remiſſe <hi>damnation</hi> in the <hi>day of Judgment</hi> then they, <hi>Mat. ch.</hi> 11. <hi>v.</hi> 22. Conſider ſecondly, the multitude of <hi>Sects</hi> lately ſprung up in the <hi>Kingdom:</hi> what diviſions, and ſubdiviſions are there known to be of the old <hi>Anaba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ptiſts;</hi> beſides the two main Factions of <hi>Presbyterians</hi> and <hi>Independents,</hi> new things and names, that have almoſt quite aboliſhed their <hi>Proteſtant Proge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitor;</hi> their zeale and number ebbing and flowing by ſucceſſe of the <hi>Sword.</hi> Some, you know, are ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent <hi>Zelots</hi> of the <hi>Scottiſh Reformation;</hi> others deteſt it as peſtiferous and hereticall: Some retain the old denomination of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> yet have much of the <hi>new Modell:</hi> Some hold <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi> eſſenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all to the true <hi>Proteſtant Church;</hi> others deny it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> holding <hi>Biſhops</hi> altogether unneceſſary to the <hi>refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med Churches;</hi> and demonſtrating it by the not being and non-uſe of them, in any <hi>Reformation,</hi> even from the beginning, out of the <hi>King</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lands</hi> Dominions. Some againe, as you know, ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of curioſity, or to prevent <hi>Penalties,</hi> frequent the <hi>Pariſh Churches</hi> on <hi>Sundayes;</hi> and on other
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:97574:10"/> dayes frequent <hi>Conventicles</hi> of another <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion,</hi> utterly deteſting that of the <hi>Pariſh Church,</hi> as ſuperſtitious or hereticall; and ſo on the <hi>Week daies</hi> outwardly diſavow the profeſſion, they avow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the <hi>Sunday.</hi> Conſider thirdly, the little re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard that is now given to the 39. <hi>Articles,</hi> hereto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the distinctive difference of the old <hi>Engliſh Proteſtant.</hi> And fourthly the queſtioning of the <hi>Apoſtles Creed,</hi> which implies a doubt of its truth, at leaſt in ſome points. Before this <hi>Parliament</hi> it was every where uſed throughout the Kingdome, as an outward profeſſion of every ones beliefe: Now it is queſtioned, and conſequently doubted of, by the <hi>Repreſentative Body</hi> of the whole Kingdome, and their <hi>Synodicall Divines;</hi> Add to this, the old true ſaying, <hi>Dubius in fide, infidelis eſt,</hi> he that doubts in matters of faith, is no right believer, and then draw you the conſequence; Put all together and you will ſee, that the queſtions I made you, are not ſo eaſily anſwerable, as perhaps you thought at the firſt.</p>
                  <p>S. <hi>Auguſtine (lib. de. haereſ.)</hi> numbereth nine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſeverall Hereſies (ſo many Reformations were they) ſprung up betwixt <hi>Chriſts</hi> time and his. i. in about four Centuries. So many more roſe betwixt S. <hi>Auguſtines</hi> daies, and <hi>Luthers.</hi> i. 180. Hereſies in 1500. yeares, according to the obſervation of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers. Betwixt <hi>Luthers</hi> apoſtacie from S. <hi>Auſtins</hi> Rule, and defection from the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> in the yeare 1517. and the year 1595. (which is but the intervall of 78) modern Authors, <hi>Staphilus, Hoſius, P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ateolus,</hi> and others do reckon 270 new Sects, all <hi>Reformations</hi> of what was ſome daies, or houres before. But if any man would number all the
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97574:10"/> 
                     <hi>Reformations,</hi> or Sects that theſe laſt 8. yeares have hatcht in <hi>England,</hi> perhaps the probableſt rule of his <hi>Arithmetick</hi> would be <hi>quot capita, tot ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae,</hi> as many opinions in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> as heads of men; no common name being to be found, ſit to comprehend our <hi>Sectaries,</hi> but that of a <hi>Suiſt,</hi> one that followes his own dreams or fancy in choice of <hi>Scripture,</hi> in the interpretation of it, and in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry particular concerning <hi>Religion,</hi> without profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of agreement or communion, which any follow, unleſſe it be the communion of <hi>non-agreement.</hi> The <hi>Scrofa Alba</hi> of <hi>Reformation</hi> hath been ſo fertile theſe later dayes, that to uſe <hi>Staniſlaus Roſcius</hi> his words <hi>(Lib. de Atheiſmis) Errans neſcit quid velit, neec quid nolit. The erring Reformer doth neither know what he would, nor what he would not:</hi> let it be but new, it ſufficeth.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>S. Hilarie (lib. ad Conſtantium &amp; Conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem Imperat.)</hi> objected as a great abſurdity a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Arrians,</hi> that they had <hi>annuas, &amp; men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruas fides,</hi> that they changed their faith once a yeare, yea once a moneth; an evident argument of their falſhood. If you will take the teſtimony of twice two or three, and compare the weekly Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons together, you may perhaps finde ſome of your <hi>Engliſh reforming Doctrines,</hi> brought to old age, and funeralls, in leſſe then a moneth. An evident demonſtration, that <hi>Reformation of Faith</hi> is not <hi>a city built on a mountaine, (Matth.</hi> 5. 14.) nor <hi>a wiſe mans houſe ſeated on a rock, (Matth.</hi> 7. 24.) but a <hi>wall raiſed and dawbed without temper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, (Ezech.</hi> 13. 11.) or a fooles cottage erected upon ſands.</p>
                  <q>
                     <lg>
                        <pb n="18" facs="tcp:97574:11"/>
                        <l> 
                           <hi>Quae pendulum ſolutae</hi>
                        </l>
                        <l>
                           <hi>Pondus ferre recuſant.</hi>
                        </l>
                     </lg>
                     <lg>
                        <l>In Hereſies unſtable ground</l>
                        <l>No ſetled footing can be found.</l>
                     </lg>
                  </q>
                  <p>And how reall that of <hi>S. Athanaſius</hi> againſt the <hi>Arrian Heretiks (Epiſt. de Nicaena Synodo)</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grees unto all the <hi>Reformers</hi> of the later dayes, I ſubmit even to their cenſures: <hi>Nunquam unam, &amp;c. They never ſtand to one and the ſame opini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, but run from one to another; now praiſing, now diſpraiſing the ſame; now condemning what they approved a little before:</hi> a true character of hereticks, and mark of falſhood.</p>
                  <p>Things then being fallen to this unconcealable con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion in <hi>England,</hi> without likelyhood of ſtop, as long as the <hi>principles</hi> of the prime <hi>Reformers</hi> ſtand ſtill in vogue; can any man wonder at the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion to <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> either of the men here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after ſpecified, or any others? for my own part, I cannot but wonder, that any man acknowledging the <hi>ſoule immortall,</hi> and that either <hi>Hell</hi> or <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> must be her <hi>eternall Domicil</hi> after this life; and with all acknowledging that a <hi>falſe Religion</hi> cannot be the way towards beatitude; ſhould ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pect a ſecond call, for his deſerting that, of whoſe falſhood in it ſelfe, damnableneſſe to mans ſoule; and inconſiſtency with an ordered <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>State,</hi> be hath ſo many, and ſo pregnant Demonstrations, as it were to the eye.</p>
                  <p>The old Proverb of the <hi>Hebrews</hi> is, <hi>Veritatem, ſtabiles; mendacium, debiles habere pedes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> that truth hath ſtrong ſtedfast, ſure footing; but a lie,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97574:11"/> onely weake, unstedfast, tottering foundations: Whence, the firſt is of a permanent perpetuall du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance; the other, eaſily ſupplanted and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwne. Were any of the <hi>Reformations</hi> that are ſo yearly, monethly, if not oftner forged, true; it would ſtand the ſame in it ſelfe, <hi>firm,</hi> and <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant,</hi> ſcorning <hi>chop</hi> and <hi>change:</hi> but ſeeing there is none that doth not loſe ground upon the firſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of a <hi>new ſpirit,</hi> none that ſuffers not in her reputation, by the credit of every <hi>gifted Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> of the new <hi>Modell,</hi> (you know how fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently <hi>new ſpirits</hi> and <hi>new gifts</hi> are pretended) certainly by the <hi>Hebreans Adage,</hi> all <hi>Reformati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons</hi> are to be esteemed, as weak grounded lies.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Nihil quod non manet in ſe ipſo, verum eſt: omne quipp<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> quod alteratur, falſitas eſt, non ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nens in ſcipſo. Nothing can be true,</hi> (ſaith that rare Prodigie of Nature <hi>Triſmegiſtus) that doth not abide the ſame conſtant in it ſelfe: every thing ſubject to alteration, is falſe:</hi> That your <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mations</hi> in <hi>England</hi> are ſubject to alterations, I need not tell you, unleſſe you be blind; that therefore they muſt of neceſſity be falſe, you may take as a ſure truth, from the pen of <hi>Triſmegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If according to the <hi>Wiſeman</hi> in his <hi>Proverbs,</hi> the later ends of ſome waies, which ſeem to a man, juſt and upright, ſo outwardly masked with mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rality of life, and good neighbourhood, as hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly diſcernable, (eſpecially by the unwary vulgar) from waies really ſure and good; do yet lead to death: how ſure of <hi>eternall death</hi> and <hi>damnation</hi> muſt he be, who runs the waies of the preſent <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation;</hi> which are ſo far from ſeeming juſt by
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97574:12"/> any obducted diſguiſe, that every man (even the greateſt ſticklers ſtick not to confeſſe it now and then among their friends) ſees them plainely full of injuſtice, impiety, oppreſſions, rebellions againſt all ſorts of humane ſuperiours, and blaſphemies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God himſelfe? certainly it is more then high time for all men to abhorr the <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>morrhe</hi> of <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> with the inunda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of vice, and corrupted manners it hath brought with it into the world.</p>
                  <p>That you may yet farther penetrate the malig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of the confuſion you are fallen into, (ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther argument that <hi>Reformation</hi> in <hi>Faith</hi> is of the ſerpent <hi>Hydras</hi> nature,) take this Corollary or addition to what is ſaid already: That it muſt be endleſſe in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and altogether re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medileſſe, as long as the old laid principles of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation,</hi> derived from <hi>Luther</hi> and <hi>Calvin,</hi> ſtand uncontrolled: there being now no way left to withstand the reforming decrees of the preſent <hi>Parliament,</hi> (from which is iſſued the main of your late alterations,) or condemne, what moſt men now judge to be amiſſe; without condemnation of what you have been approving &amp; abetting ever ſince your firſt revolt from the <hi>Pope</hi> and <hi>Roman Church.</hi> For a clearer explication of my mind, give me leave I pray, with your patience, to propoſe you ſome queſtions.</p>
                  <q>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Sic volo; ſic jubeo; ſit pro ratione voluntas,</hi>
                     </p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>I ſo will have it; ſo command;</l>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>My will muſt for a reaſon ſtand.</l> 
                  </q>
                  <pb n="21" facs="tcp:97574:12"/>
                  <p> When others failed, this was one of <hi>Luthers</hi> Lawes, to ſet forward his fanaticall <hi>Reformation</hi> againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> and <hi>Catholike Church.</hi> Why may not the <hi>Parliament,</hi> the <hi>Repreſentative Body</hi> of a <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> uſe it with more authority then <hi>Luther,</hi> one ſingle private man? If you allow the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the uſe of ſuch a <hi>legiſlative Power;</hi> you muſt not condemne the ſeque<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> that do naturally flow out of it: you muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> to all their <hi>Orders</hi> and <hi>Ordinances,</hi> how irrationall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> they ſeem to private perſons. If you condemn it in the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> (look well to it) through their ſides, you condemne it <hi>à fortiori</hi> in <hi>Luther,</hi> and ſo you crack the pate and credit of your <hi>grand Reformer,</hi> who ſo inſultingly uſed it, and whom you have been ſo long upholding for a Saint.</p>
                  <p>But to inſiſt no longer on that extravagant prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple. The ſpecious pretence of <hi>Reformation</hi> will ſo juſtifie the preſent <hi>Parliaments</hi> actions (ſeem they never ſo new or paradoxicall) that you ſhall hardly question them, without ſubverſion of the whole Fabrick of your late <hi>Reformation.</hi> For ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample, tell me why may not this preſent <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> caſhiere the <hi>Ordination of Miniſters,</hi> inven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted onely in <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixths daies; as well as thoſe of his time, caſhiered the manner of <hi>Ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,</hi> they then found in being and vigour, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any knowne beginning of it ſince the <hi>Apoſtles?</hi> Why may not this <hi>Parliament</hi> degrade the now pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended <hi>Biſhops,</hi> made onely according to that <hi>new Modell,</hi> and onely authorized by <hi>Parliament;</hi> why not devest them of their Peerage, cast them out of their government, and levell them to the rank of ordinary men; as well as other <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97574:13"/> cast out the old <hi>Biſhops,</hi> conſecrated after the manner of the whole <hi>Chriſtian World,</hi> and who were never pretended to have their <hi>ſpirituall authority</hi> from <hi>Parliament,</hi> nor to be invested in their dignitie by uſurpation of any other mans right; cast them out (I ſay) of their Seas of Government, their Seats in <hi>Parliament,</hi> out of their meanes, and liberty, into poverty and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon? Why not trench on all mens proprieties, and violently deſpoile them of their fortunes; as well as former times for <hi>Reformation</hi> ſake, impropria<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to themſelves the <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Abby-lands</hi> from their firſt true owners, casting the <hi>Monks Friers</hi> and vowed <hi>Nuns</hi> a begging into the world? <hi>D. Carier</hi> obſerved (nor did he alone) that <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Abbey lands</hi> did ſeldome thrive with their <hi>new holders.</hi> If (I tell you now) that the preſent ruine of a flouriſhing Kingdome is but the naturall off-spring of the old injurious depopulati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Abbies,</hi> you will hardly know how to refute me.</p>
                  <p>Why may not this preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> damne the <hi>Common Prayer Book</hi> first invented in <hi>Edward</hi> the ſixths daies, and afterwards confirmed by Act of <hi>Parliament</hi> in Q. <hi>Elizabeths</hi> Raigne, ſince the birth of many now alive, (no long preſcription) as well as thoſe of their times, damned the <hi>Maſſe,</hi> which was as ancient in <hi>England,</hi> and generally throughout the world, as <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> it ſelfe? Why may not <hi>King Charles</hi> that now is, (whom I honour and love from my heart, as it is the duty of all Subjects to do in whatſoever Countrey they live) overthrow the <hi>Reformation,</hi> he ſwore at his <hi>Coronation</hi> to maintain, as well as King
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:97574:13"/> 
                     <hi>Henry</hi> the eighth and Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> introdu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their ſeverall <hi>Reformations,</hi> contrary to the <hi>old Religion</hi> which they found in the Kingdome, and ſwore at their <hi>Coronations,</hi> to preſerve, with all her <hi>Rights, Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Priviledges?</hi> would <hi>King Charles</hi> be more perjured then they, or his perjury worſe then theirs? why may not this <hi>Parliament,</hi> yea particular Subjects, rebell a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>Soveraigne</hi> for a better <hi>Reformation;</hi> as well as the <hi>Lutherans</hi> in <hi>Germany</hi> rebelled a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their Soveraigne <hi>Charles</hi> the fifth, to bring in their <hi>Reformation,</hi> and to aboliſh <hi>Popery;</hi> or (to omit others, all applauded juſtified and abet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by thoſe of the <hi>reformed Churches)</hi> as the <hi>Scots</hi> rebelled for the ſame end, againſt Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> our <hi>Kings Grandmother,</hi> afterward be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>headed in purſuance of the ſame cauſe? you tell me I do <hi>C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>me<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>m movere.</hi> I deſiſt with the propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall of one onely question more; when the preſent <hi>Agitators</hi> of <hi>Reformation</hi> have purged themſelves of all the <hi>pretended Religion</hi> they had eight or nine yeares ago, and raiſed their work to a high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er pitch then they have <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> thought on; will it not ſtill be ſubject to a <hi>Babilonian</hi> confuſion? Why may not the children of the preſent <hi>Reformers</hi> cut the throats of their fathers, and condemne them for ignorants or ſuperſtitious, and reſcind all the Acts of their predeceſſours, for a better <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation,</hi> according to their new ſpirits, as well as theſe preſent cut the throats of their forefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, undoing at a breath what bad been ſo long a doing in the Kingdome.</p>
                  <q>
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:97574:14"/>
                     <l> Damnoſa quid non imminuit dies?</l>
                     <l>Aetas parentum pejor avis, tulit</l>
                     <l>Nos nequiores: mox datura</l>
                     <l>Progeniem vitioſiorem.</l>
                     <bibl>Joel ch. 1.</bibl> 
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <l>Where Grandſires <hi>Erukes</hi> are; their iſſue may</l>
                     <l>Wild <hi>Locuſts</hi> prove; next comes, in <hi>Joels</hi> liſt;</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Bruke;</hi> a plague of worſe, and greater ſway:</l>
                     <l>And what comes then? a <hi>blaſt,</hi> or burning miſt.</l>
                     <l>Thus men, in tract of time, from bad do fall,</l>
                     <l>To what is worſe; from worſe, to worſt of all.</l> 
                  </q>
                  <p>To pretend that, what the preſent or paſt <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> did, was all done for the truth, for the glory of the Lord, for the light and liberty of the Goſpell, to aboliſh <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtition:</hi> to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nthrone <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> the <hi>whore of Babylon,</hi> the Beaſt of the <hi>Apocalyps,</hi> and the like; is more then childiſh ſimplicity; there is no <hi>Reformer</hi> ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getfull or ſtupid, but by his ſpirit pretends <hi>Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture,</hi> the <hi>glory of the Lord,</hi> the light and liberty of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> the planting of <hi>ſaving truth,</hi> &amp;c. and whoſoever is oppoſite to his ſpirit, is <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> the <hi>Whore of Babylon,</hi> the <hi>Beaſt</hi> of the <hi>Apoca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lypſe,</hi> and therefore muſt be pulled down whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he be. Nor can it availe at any time, to ſay, that hitherto the <hi>work of Reformation</hi> hath been in <hi>fieri,</hi> or in doing; (as ſome ſay, <hi>Qu. Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beths broome did not ſweep clean)</hi> but now is in <hi>facto eſſe:</hi> Now it is come to a <hi>Non plus ul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tra,</hi> perfected beyond all addition or alteration: this, I ſay, can never availe, nor ſtop the confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions; as long as the <hi>reforming private ſpirits,</hi> for the pretences already ſpecified, (which will never be at an end) or the <hi>Calvinian Doctrine</hi> of <hi>Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination</hi> ſayes, No.</p>
                  <pb n="25" facs="tcp:97574:14"/>
                  <p> Perhaps the preſent pretended <hi>Biſhops,</hi> and the <hi>Party</hi> ſuffering with them, may ſay, <hi>The old Reformations againſt the</hi> Catholikes <hi>were good and neceſſary, but the meanes uſed to begin and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mote them, naught, and not to be imitated: And that if there be any farther Reformation to bee made, it muſt not be by proſecution of the old un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lawfull meanes.</hi> Their ſuffering by the meanes u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed for the preſent further <hi>Reformation,</hi> makes them condemne the old. This comes now too late: they ſhould have condemned them long ago, before their teſtimony became invalidated by their private intereſt. Certainly <hi>Luther</hi> and the firſt late <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers</hi> never acknowledged the meanes they uſed, to be naught or unlawfull. And why ſhould wee think the preſent or future <hi>Reformer</hi> will ever hold the meanes neceſſary for his ends, unlawfull? Endleſſe then is the confuſion of <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State</hi> in <hi>England</hi> to be; no end of ſticklings and rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions; no end of our wounds and bloudſhed; no in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance more intailed upon our poſterity, then violation of <hi>humane</hi> and <hi>divine Lawes;</hi> nothing more certain then eternall damnation of mens ſouls, as long as the firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> principles ſtand in force, and their <hi>Reformations</hi> applauded.</p>
                  <p>Behold more then ſufficient cauſe, not onely, not to wonder at the late <hi>converſion</hi> of divers learned <hi>Schollers</hi> to the <hi>Roman Fai<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>h;</hi> but to admire that more do not follow their examples. Behold more then ſufficient cauſe, for thoſe that pretend to any feare of God, or care of their own ſoules, by re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gard to <hi>Religion,</hi> or <hi>manners,</hi> to the ſpirituall or politike weale, utterly to anathematize all <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mation</hi> in <hi>Faith,</hi> with the damnable principles of
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97574:15"/> the late <hi>Reformers,</hi> the ſources of all the evills our <hi>Kingdome</hi> now groanes under. Conſequently behold more then ſufficient cauſe, for all to rank themſelves into the number of <hi>Catholikes,</hi> who have now the ſame <hi>unchanged Religion</hi> they had before this preſent <hi>Parliament;</hi> and then had the ſame they had in the reigne of <hi>K. James, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>u. Eliza<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beth, Qu. Mary, K. Edward</hi> 6. and <hi>Henry</hi> the 8. in whoſe dayes the <hi>Reformation</hi> was commenced in <hi>Germany,</hi> and through too generall a looſeneſſe in manners, and, deſire of ſenſuall liberty, began to creep into <hi>England,</hi> as all Hiſtories can evidence unto you. Nor can any deſire a more pregnant te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony of our being now, and in former dayes of the ſame Faith, without variation of one tit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle; then our reformed Adverſaries are ready to afford us, who have for the times paſt, and ſtill doe perſecute us, not as new <hi>Sactaries</hi> with old Lawes, but with new <hi>Statutes</hi> for <hi>non-conformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> to their new <hi>Reformation,</hi> and for our conſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy to the profeſſion of our forefathers: from which had we ſtincht but the breadth of a naile, and taken upon us ſome new denomination, we had been as hard to be found out as other <hi>Sectaries,</hi> and as free from penalties as they: which forefathers of ours, living (before <hi>Luthers</hi> dayes) in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with the <hi>Catholikes</hi> of <hi>France, Spaine, I<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talic,</hi> and all the <hi>Chriſtian world,</hi> as we do now, did deliver faithfully (it ſtood upon their ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation ſo to do) unto their children (thoſe of the reſt of the <hi>Chriſtian World</hi> did the like unto their children) that <hi>Depoſitum</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity,</hi> which they had received from their predeceſſors, and they from theirs, by a continued ſucceſſive line of Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97574:15"/> from the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Chriſt;</hi> no reform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing enemy being able to ſhew, when the <hi>Catholike Faith</hi> now profeſſed by us, and perſecuted in us, began in the world, nor when the ſucceſſive Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition we and all <hi>Catholikes</hi> pretend unto, was intercepted; an infallible argument of our perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted Religions being from the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> &amp; <hi>Chriſt.</hi> More then ſufficient cauſe, I ſay, for all to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn to the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> ſetled by <hi>Chriſt</hi> the divine Architect, upon a rock never to be prevai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led againſt by humane or Devills powers, never ſubject to fall from her ſelf in points of faith, nor conſequently to be reformed in them, from which <hi>Church</hi> your firſt <hi>Reformers</hi> fell, <hi>Ex nobis ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euntes</hi> (one of the marks by which we are to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern Hereticks, as the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> teach us in their <hi>Acts,</hi> chap. 15. ver. 24.) going out from among us, to gain ſenſuall liberty to themſelves, to be reven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged on their ſuperiors, or for private by-ends: <hi>troubling the world with words, ſubverting mens ſoules, without commiſſion or mandate</hi> from any ſuperior for their facts, or pretended Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.</p>
                  <p>And finally, cauſe enough, for the world to reflect how ill adviſed they were in times paſt, and what an ill preſident they ſhewed poſterity, in their former greedy acceptance of new reforming ſpirits, ſo prejudiciall to ſaving truth, to order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly government in <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State,</hi> and to parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular mens properties. And withall, to take warning for the future, not to remit the work of <hi>Reformation,</hi> even in things ſubject thereunto; as Ceremonies, humane practices, manners, and the like, to every giddy pretending ſpirit, (if
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97574:16"/> you do ſo, you ſhall certainly have more holes made then mended) but to ſuch as are lawfully ordered and commiſſioned for it by the <hi>viſible Church,</hi> the <hi>pillar and ground of truth,</hi> that all things be done according to her preſcript, <hi>honeſtè &amp; ſecundum ordinem,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 40.</p>
                  <p>But fearing, lest I ſhould make this Prefatory Diſcourſe like the gates of the City <hi>Myndus,</hi> or like a great portall to a little houſe, I'le firſt preſent you with the names of ſome late <hi>Converts,</hi> and then deteine you no longer from my promiſed re-impreſſion of <hi>Doctor Cariers</hi> learned Letter to <hi>King James,</hi> which is here rendred <hi>verbatim</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the Originall, excepting onely the additi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of ſome few marginall Notes; I deſire you to read it with attention, reflecting from thoſe, to theſe times, and not permit your mind to bee ſo prejudicate, as to give cenſure, before you have well pondered the matter, the ſcope of which <hi>(mutato tempore)</hi> is the ſame with this, which comes from one, who unfeignedly would have <hi>all men ſaved, and come to the knowledge of,</hi> and imbrace <hi>the truth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>N. STRANGE.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>From</hi> Paris
<date>1. <hi>Novemb.</hi> 1648. ſtylo novo.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL.</hi> 2.</bibl>
                     <q>
                        <p>Et nunc Reges intelligite: erudimini qui judicatis terram. Attendite diſciplinam, nè—pereatis.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97574:16"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>The names of ſome who have lately been</hi> Miniſters, <hi>or <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity men in</hi> Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land <hi>and</hi> Scotland, <hi>and are now converted to the</hi> Catholike Faith.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tho. Vane,</hi> Doctor of Divinity of <hi>Chriſts Colledge Cambridge,</hi> lately Chaplain Extraordinary to His Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty, and Parſon of <hi>Crayford</hi> in <hi>Kent.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Hugh Paulin de Creſſy,</hi> of <hi>Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bridge,</hi> lately Prebend of <hi>Windſore</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> and Deane of <hi>Laghlin</hi> in <hi>Ireland,</hi> now entred into the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious Order of S. <hi>Benedict</hi> at <hi>Doway.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97574:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p> 
                     <hi>Hen. Ireſon</hi> of <hi>All-Soules Oxford,</hi> Doctor of the Civill Law.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>N. Read</hi> of <hi>New Colledge Oxford,</hi> Doctor of the Civill Law.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Rich. Nicholls</hi> Bachelor of Divinity, of <hi>Peter-houſe Cambridge.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Rich. Craſhaw,</hi> Maſter of Arts of <hi>Peter-houſe Cambridge,</hi> now Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretary to a Cardinall in <hi>Rome,</hi> well known in England for his excellent and ingenious <hi>Poems.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>William Rowlands</hi> Miniſter of S. <hi>Margarets Westminſter,</hi> Maſter of Arts of <hi>Exeter Colledge Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Tho. Normington,</hi> Maſter of Arts of <hi>Pembroke Hall Cambridge,</hi> now in <hi>Italy,</hi> a very able man in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Sciences.</p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:97574:17"/>
                  <p> Mr. <hi>Joyner</hi> Bachelor of Arts, and Fellow of S. <hi>Mary Magdelens</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Oxford.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Blakiſton</hi> Bachelor of Arts of <hi>Cambridge,</hi> who died laſt yeare in the Engliſh Colledge at <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Edward Barker</hi> of <hi>Caius</hi> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge <hi>Cambridge,</hi> Bachelor of Arts.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Eaton</hi> of Cambridge, now Prieſt in the Engliſh Colledge at <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Peter Glu,</hi> Miniſter, of <hi>Balli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oll</hi> Colledge in <hi>Oxford,</hi> now Prieſt.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Jackſon</hi> Miniſter.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Cooper.</hi> Miniſter.</p>
                  <p>Mr. <hi>Daniel</hi> Miniſter, now entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Religious Order.</p>
                  <div type="subpart">
                     <pb facs="tcp:97574:18"/>
                     <head>Of Scots.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> John Chrighton, <hi>a famous man in his Country, late Preacher of</hi> Parſon <hi>in</hi> Scotland, <hi>afterwards emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent in</hi> Languedos, <hi>and laſtly Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lain to the Marqueſſe of</hi> Ormond.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Andrew Youngſton <hi>late Regent of</hi> Aberdein, <hi>now in a Colledge in</hi> Spain.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> William Simple <hi>late Regent in</hi> Glaſcow <hi>now alſo in</hi> Spain.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Hugh Roſſe <hi>late Regent in</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berdein, <hi>now alſo in</hi> Spain.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mr.</hi> Tho. Johnſton, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:97574:18" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                     <p> Beſides theſe, there are divers both learned and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned, lately entred in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to Communion with the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> whoſe names you may more eaſily learne, then I diſcreetly pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh. Nor do I doubt but one more commerced with <hi>England Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with other parts of <hi>France,</hi> and with the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of the <hi>low Countries</hi> might eaſily furniſh you with a larger Catalogue of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertites,</hi> of as good fame
<pb facs="tcp:97574:19"/> for their learning, and good parts in your <hi>Univerſities,</hi> and in their reſpective coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries, as theſe I have been bold to name: their underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding being now better diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed to diſcern and reflect upon their former errours, by the palpable confuſion and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſciable effects they ſaw e-every where ſprouted and ſprouting out of the late <hi>Reformation</hi> begun by <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:97574:19"/>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="errata">
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:97574:20"/>
                     <head>Errata <hi>in the Preface.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>PAge 6. line 13. read <hi>pretence</hi> of. p. 12. l. 6. r. <hi>the</hi> bread. &amp; l. ult. r. of <hi>a</hi> little.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>ERRATA.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>PAge</hi> 3. <hi>line</hi> 28. <hi>read</hi> title. <hi>p.</hi> 7. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>dele one</hi> at. <hi>p.</hi> 11. <hi>l.</hi> 15. <hi>dele</hi> in. <hi>p.</hi> 21. <hi>l.</hi> 24. <hi>r.</hi> ſwinge over. <hi>p.</hi> 23. <hi>l.</hi> 13. <hi>r. in</hi> theſe. <hi>p.</hi> 39. <hi>l. ult. r.</hi> reaſonable.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Other leſſe materiall faults, with ſome falſe pointings, the diſcerning</hi> Reader <hi>will eaſily diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver and correct.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:97574:20"/>
                  <head>Moſt Excellent, and renowned Soveraign,</head>
                  <p>IT is not unknown to all that know me in <hi>England,</hi> that for theſe many years I have had my health very ill: And therfore having from time to time uſed all the meanes and medicines that <hi>England</hi> could afford; last of all by the advice of my Phyſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tians, I have made it my humble ſuit unto <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> that I might travell unto the <hi>Spa</hi> for the uſe of thoſe waters; purpoſing with my ſelf, that if I could be well, I would go from thence to <hi>Heydel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berg,</hi> and ſpend this winter there. But when I was gone from the <hi>Spa</hi> to <hi>Aquiſgrane,</hi> and ſo to <hi>Colein,</hi> I found my ſelf rather worſe, then better then I was before: And therefore I reſolved with my ſelf, that it was high time for me to ſettle my thoughts upon another world. And ſeeing I was out of hope to enjoy the health of my body, at the last to look to the health of my ſoule, from whence both Art and experience teach me, that all my bodi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infirmities have their beginning: For if I could by any ſtudy have proved <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> to be falſe, or by any means have profeſſed it to be true in <hi>England,</hi> I doubt not but the contentment of my ſoule would have much helped the health of my body. But the more I ſtudied the <hi>Scriptures</hi> and most <hi>ancient Fathers</hi> to confute it, the more I was compelled to ſee the truth thereof. And the more I laboured to reconcile the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>England</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto, the more I was diſliked, ſuspected and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned as a common enemy. And if I would have been either ignorant or ſilent, I might perhaps with the pleaſures and commodities of my preferments,
<pb facs="tcp:97574:21"/> have in time cast off the care of <hi>Religion.</hi> But ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing my ſtudy forced me to know, and my place com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled me to preach, I had no way to avoid my grief, nor any means to indure it. I have therefore appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended the opportunity of my Licence to travell, that I may withdraw my ſelf for a while from the ſight and offence of thoſe in <hi>England,</hi> who hate <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> and freely and fully enioy the preſence of our <hi>B. Saviour,</hi> in the Unity of his <hi>Catholike Church;</hi> wherein I will never forget at the daily Oblation of his most <hi>B. Body</hi> and <hi>Blood,</hi> to lift up my heart unto him, and to pray for the admiſsion of <hi>your Majeſty</hi> thereunto. And in the meane time, I have thought it my duty to write this ſhort <hi>Treatiſe</hi> with my own hand; wherein, before I publiſh my ſelf to the world, I deſire to ſhew to <hi>your Majeſty</hi> theſe two things. 1. <hi>The means of my converſion unto</hi> Catholike Religion. 2. <hi>The hopes I have to do</hi> your Majesty <hi>no ill ſervice therein.</hi> I humbly crave <hi>your Majeſties</hi> pardon, and will rest ever,</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>
                        <hi>Your Majeſties faithfull, and truly devoted Servant,</hi> B. Carier.</signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Liege</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Decemb.</hi> 12. 1613.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div n="1" type="chapter">
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:97574:21"/>
                  <head>CHAP. I. <hi>The meanes of my Converſion to the</hi> Catholike Religion.</head>
                  <p>I Muſt confeſſe, to Gods honour, and my owne ſhame, that if it had been in my power to chooſe, I would never have been a <hi>Catholike.</hi> I was born and brought up in <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and was taught to abhor a <hi>Papist</hi> as much as any <hi>Puritan</hi> in <hi>England</hi> doth. I had ever a great deſire to juſtifie the <hi>Religion</hi> of the State, and had great hope to advance my ſelf thereby. Neither was my hope ever ſo great, as by your <hi>Majesties</hi> favour it was at the very inſtant of my reſolution for <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> and the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment I had, together with the honour of <hi>your Majesties</hi> ſervice, was greater by much; then without <hi>your Majesties</hi> favour, I look for in this world. But though I was as ambitious of <hi>your Maiesties</hi> favour, and as deſirous of the honours and pleaſures of my Countrey, as any man that is therein, yet ſeeing that I was not like any long while to injoy them, and if I ſhould for my private commodity ſpeak, or write, or do any thing againſt the honour of <hi>Christ</hi> his <hi>Church,</hi> and againſt the evidence of my owne conſcience, I muſt ſhortly appeare before the ſame <hi>Christ,</hi> in the preſence of the ſame his <hi>Church,</hi> to give an account thereof. Therfore I neither durſt any further purſue my own deſire of honour, nor hazard my ſoule any farther in the juſtification of that <hi>Religion,</hi> which I ſaw was impoſſible to be ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified by any ſuch reaſon, as at the day of Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment would go for payment; and that it may ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare that I have not reſpected any thing ſo much
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:97574:22"/> in this world, as my duty to your Majeſtie, and my love to my friends and Countrey, I humbly beſeech <hi>your Majesty</hi> to give me leave, as briefly as I can, to recount unto you the whole courſe of my ſtudies, and indeavours in this kind, even from the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of my life untill this preſent.</p>
                  <p>2. I was born in the Year, 1566. being the ſon of <hi>Ant. Carier,</hi> a learned and devout man, who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though he were a <hi>Protestant,</hi> and a <hi>Preacher,</hi> yet he did ſo ſeaſon me with the Principles of Piety and Devotion, as I could not chooſe but ever ſince be very zealous in matters of <hi>Religion.</hi> Of him I learned that all falſe Religions in the world, were but Policies invented of men, for the temporall ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Princes and States; and therefore that they were divers, and alwaies changeable, according to the divers reaſons and occaſions of State. But true <hi>Christian Religion</hi> was a truth revealed of God, for the eternall ſalvation of ſoules, and therefore was like to God, alwaies one and the ſame: So that all the Princes and States in the world never have been, nor ſhall be able to overthrow that <hi>Religion.</hi> This to me ſeemed an excellent ground, for the finding out of that Religion, wherein a man might find reſt for his ſoule, which cannot be ſatisfied with any thing but eternall truth.</p>
                  <p>3. My next care then was, after I came to years of diſcretion, by all the beſt meanes I could, to in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme my ſelfe, whether the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>England</hi> were indeed the very ſame, which being prefigured and propheſied in the <hi>Old Testament,</hi> was perfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted by our <hi>B. Saviour,</hi> and delivered to his <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles</hi> and <hi>Diſciples</hi> to continue, by perpetuall ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſion in his <hi>viſible Church,</hi> untill his coming a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine: or whether it were a new one, for private
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:97574:22"/> purpoſes of Stateſmen invented, and by humane Lawes eſtabliſhed. Of this I could not chuſe but make ſome doubt, becauſe I heard men talk much in thoſe dayes of the change of Religion which was then lately made in the beginning of <hi>Q. Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeths</hi> Reign.</p>
                  <p>4. I was ſorry to heare of change, and of a <hi>new Religion,</hi> ſeeing me thought in reaſon, if true <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> were eternall, then new <hi>Religion</hi> could not be true. But yet I hoped that the <hi>Religion</hi> of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> was not a change, or new <hi>Religion,</hi> but a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution of the old; and that the change was in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> which in proceſſe of time might perhaps grow to be ſuperſtitious, and idolatrous; and therefore that <hi>England</hi> had done well to leave the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and to reform it ſelf; and for this purpoſe I did at my leiſure and beſt oportunity, as I came to more judgment, read over the <hi>Chronicles of England,</hi> and obſerved all the alterations of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion that I could find therein: But when I found there, that the preſent <hi>Religion of England</hi> was a plain <note n="*" place="margin">What then is it now!</note> change, and change upon change, and that there was no cauſe at all of the firſt, but onely that <hi>K. Henry</hi> 8. was deſirous to change his old Bed-fellow, that he might leave ſome heires male behind him (for belike hee feared that Females would not be able to withſtand the tile of <hi>Scot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,)</hi> and that the change was continued and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſed by the poſterity of his later wives, I could not chooſe but ſuſpect ſomthing; but yet the love of the world, and hope of preferment would not ſuffer me to believe, but that all was well, and as it ought to be.</p>
                  <p>5. Thus I ſatisfied my ſelf at School, and ſtudi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:97574:23"/> the Arts and Phyloſophy, and other humane learning, untill being <hi>Master of Arts,</hi> and Fellow of <hi>Corpus Christi Colledge</hi> in <hi>Cambridge,</hi> I was at the laſt, by the Statutes of that Houſe, called to the ſtudie of Divinity, and bound to take upon me the order of <hi>Priesthood:</hi> then I thought it my duty, for the better ſatisfaction of my owne ſoule, and the ſaving of other mens, to look as farre into the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter as poſſible I could, that I might find out the truth. And having the oportunity of a very good <hi>Library</hi> in that <hi>Colledge,</hi> I reſolved with my ſelfe to ſtudy hard, &amp; ſetting aſide all reſpect of men then alive, or of Writers that had moved or mainteined controverſies (farther then to underſtand the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion which was betwixt them) I fell to my prayers, and be took my ſelfe wholly to the reading of the <hi>Church History,</hi> and of the <hi>Ancient Fathers,</hi> which had no intereſt in either ſide; and eſpecially I made choice of <hi>S. Augustine,</hi> becauſe I hoped to find moſt comfort in him for the confirming of our <hi>Religion,</hi> and the confuting of the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>6. In this ſort I ſpent my time continually for many yeares, and noted downe whatſoever I could gather, or rather ſnatch either from the <hi>Scriptures</hi> or the <hi>Fathers</hi> to ſerve my turne. But when, after all my paines and deſire to ſerve my ſelfe, of Anti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, I found the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> to be every where confirmed, and by moſt profound demonſtrations out of holy <hi>Scripture,</hi> made moſt agreeable to the truth of <hi>Christs Goſpel,</hi> and moſt conformable to all Chriſtians ſoules, and ſaw the <hi>current</hi> opinions of our great <hi>Preachers</hi> to be eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where confuted, either in plaine termes, or by moſt unanſwerable conſequence, although my un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding was thereby greatly edified, (for which
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:97574:23"/> I had great cauſe to render immortall thanks to our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> who by theſe meanes had vouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſafed to ſhew himſelfe unto me) yet my heart was much grieved, that I muſt be faine either not preach at all, or elſe to croſse and varie from the Doctrine, which I ſaw was commonly received.</p>
                  <p>7. Being thus perplexed with my ſelf what courſe I were beſt to take, I reflected back againe upon the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and becauſe moſt of thoſe <hi>Preachers,</hi> who drew the people after them in thoſe daies were <hi>Puritans,</hi> and had grounded their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vinity upon <hi>Calvins Institutions,</hi> I thought perad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture that they, having gotten the multitude on their ſide, might wrong the <hi>Church of England</hi> in her Doctrine, as well as they deſired to doe in her Diſcipline, which indeed upon due ſearch I found to be moſt true; For I found the <hi>Common-Prayer Booke</hi> and the <hi>Catechiſmes</hi> therein contained, to hold no point of Doctrine expreſly contrary to An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity, but only that it was very defective, and contained not enough. And that for the Doctrine of <hi>Predestination, Sacraments, Grace, Free-will, Sin, &amp;c.</hi> the new <hi>Catechiſmes</hi> and Sermons of thoſe Preachers, did run wholly againſt the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Prayer Book</hi> and <hi>Catechiſmes</hi> therein, and did make as little account of the Doctrine eſtabliſhed by Law, as they did of the Diſcipline; but in the one they found oppoſition by thoſe that had private In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt, in the other they laid what they liſt, becauſe no man thought himſelfe hurt.</p>
                  <p>8. This truely was a great increaſe of my griefe, for knowing divers of thoſe Preachers to be very honeſt men, and ſuch as I did love with all my heart, I was exceeding loath to diſcent from them in private, much more loath to oppoſe them in pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like.
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:97574:24"/> And yet ſeeing I muſt needs preach, I was loatheſt of all to oppugne my own conſcience toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the faith wherein I was baptized, and the ſoules of thoſe to whom I preached. Nevertheleſse having gotten this ground to worke upon, I began to comfort my ſelfe with hope to prove, that the <hi>Religion</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law in <hi>England,</hi> was the ſame, at the leaſt in part, which now was and ever had been held in the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> the defects whereof might be ſupplied whenſoever it ſhould pleaſe God to move <hi>your Maiesty</hi> thereunto, without abrogating of that, which was already by Law e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed, which I ſtill pray for, and am not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether out of hope to ſee; and therefore I thought it my duty, as far as I durſt, rather by charitable conſtructions to reconcile things that ſeemed dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent, that ſo our ſoules might for ever be ſaved in unity, then by malicious calumniations to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine quarrells, that ſo mens turnes might for a time be ſerved in diſsention.</p>
                  <p>9. In this courſe although I did never proceed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny further then Law would give me leave, yet I al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies found the <hi>Puritanes</hi> and <hi>Calvinists,</hi> and all the Creatures of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> to be my utter enemies, who were alſo like the Sonnes of <hi>Zerviah,</hi> too ſtrong for <hi>David</hi> himſelfe, but I well perceived that all temperate and underſtanding men, who had no Intereſt in the <hi>Schiſme,</hi> were glad to hear the truth honeſtly and plainely preached unto them. And my hope was, that by patience and continuance, I ſhould in the end unmaske Hypocriſie, and gaine credit to the comfortable Doctrine of Antiquity, even a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt thoſe alſo, who out of miſinformation and prejudice did as yet moſt diſlike it. And conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring with my ſelfe, that your Right to the Crowne
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:97574:24"/> came only from <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and was ancienter then the <hi>Schiſme,</hi> which would very faine have ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terly extinguiſhed it; and that both your diſpoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by nature, your amity with <hi>Catholike Princes,</hi> your <hi>Speeches,</hi> and your <hi>Proclamations</hi> did at the beginning all tend to peace and unity, I hoped that this endeavour of mine, to inforce <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> at the leaſt as far as the <hi>Common<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Prayer Booke</hi> and <hi>Catechiſme</hi> would give me leave, ſhould be well accepted of <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and be as an In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>troduction unto farther peace and unity with the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>10. But when after my long hope, I at at the laſt did plainely perceive, that God for our ſins had ſuffered the Devill, the Author of diſſention, ſo far to prevaile, as partly by the furious practiſe of ſome deſperate <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and partly by the fiery ſugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtions of all violent <hi>Puritans,</hi> he had quite diver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted that peaceable and temperate courſe, which was hoped for, and that I muſt now either alter my judgement, which was impoſſible, or preach againſt my conſcience, which was untolerable: Lord, what anxiety and diſtraction of ſoule did I ſuffer day and night, what ſtrife betwixt my judgement, which was wholly for the peace and unity of the <hi>Church,</hi> and my affection, which was wholly to injoy the favour of <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and the love of my Friends and Countrey. This griefe of ſoule growing now deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perate, did ſtill more and more increaſe the infirmi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of my body, and yet I was ſo loath to become a profeſſed <hi>Catholike</hi> with the diſpleaſure of <hi>your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> and of all my honourable and loving friends, as I rather deſired to ſilence my judgement, with the profits and pleaſures of the world, which was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore me, then to ſatisfie it with reconciling my ſelfe
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:97574:25"/> unto the <hi>Catholike Church;</hi> But it was Gods will, that ever (as I was about to forget the care of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> and to ſettle my ſelfe to the world among my neighbours) I met with ſuch humors, as I ſaw by their violence againſt <hi>Catholikes</hi> and <hi>Catholike Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> were like to waken my ſoule by torture, ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther then bring it aſleep by temper. And therefore I was driven to recoile to God, and to his Church, that I might find reſt unto my ſoule.</p>
                  <p>11. And yet becauſe I had heard often, that the practiſe of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> was contrary to her Doctrine, I thought good to make one triall more before I reſolved; and therefore having the advice of diverſe learned Phyſitians to goe to the <hi>Spa</hi> for the health of my body, I thought good to make a vertue of neceſſity, and to get leave to go the rather for the ſatisfaction of my ſoule, hoping to find ſome greater offence in the Service of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> then I had done in her Bookes, that ſo I might returne better contented to perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute and abhorre the <hi>Catholikes</hi> at home, after I ſhould find them ſo wicked and Idolatrous abroad, as they were in every Pulpit in <hi>England</hi> affirmed to be. For this purpoſe before I would frequent their <hi>Churches,</hi> I talked with ſuch learned men as I could meet withall, and did of purpoſe diſpute againſt them, and with all the wit and learning I had, I did both juſtifie the Doctrine of <hi>England,</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law, and object the Superſtition and Idolatry which I thought they might commit, either with the <hi>Images</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> or with the <hi>Sacrament</hi> of the <hi>Altar.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>12. Their common anſwer was, that which by experience I now find to be true, viz. that they doe abhorre all <hi>Idolatry</hi> and <hi>Superſtition,</hi> and do dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97574:25"/> admoniſh the people to take heed thereof. And that they uſe <hi>Images</hi> for no other purpoſe, but only for a devout memory and repreſentation of the <hi>Church</hi> Triumphant, which is moſt ſit to be made in the time and place of prayer, where after a more ſpeciall manner, we ſhould with all reverence have our converſation amongſt the <hi>Saints</hi> in <hi>Heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And for the <hi>B. Sacrament,</hi> they do not worſhip the <hi>Accidents,</hi> which they ſee, but the ſubſtance which they believe; and ſurely if <hi>Chriſt</hi> be there truly and really preſent (as <hi>your Majeſty</hi> ſeems to grant he is) he is as much to be worſhipped, as if we ſaw him with our bodily eyes; Neither is there any more Idolatry in the one, then in the other. If our <hi>B. Saviour</hi> himſelf ſhould viſibly appeare in perſon, as he was upon the earth, <hi>Jewes</hi> and <hi>Infidells</hi> would hold it for Idolatry to worſhip him, and would crucifie him again; and ſo would all <hi>Heretikes</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, who refuſe to worſhip him in the <hi>Sacrament,</hi> where he is really preſent.</p>
                  <p>13. After divers other objections which I made, not ſo much becauſe I was not, as becauſe I deſired not to be ſatisfied, I came to the <hi>Popes</hi> ſuppoſed pride and tyranny over <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Princes,</hi> and told them of the moſt horrible Treaſon intended and practiſed by <hi>Catholikes</hi> againſt <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> which hath not yet been judicially condemned by the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> They all ſeemed to abhor the fact, as much as the beſt Subjects in the world, and much more to favor, and defend the authority of their <hi>Kings</hi> and <note place="margin">Witneſſe their loyalty to the King in theſe late warres.</note> 
                     <hi>Princes,</hi> then <hi>Hereticks</hi> do. And they ſaid, that although <hi>your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty</hi> were out of the <hi>Church,</hi> yet they doubted not, but if com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plaint
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97574:26"/> were made in a Judiciall proceeding, that fact ſhould be judicially condemned. In the mean time it was ſufficient that all <hi>Catholike Writers</hi> did con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demne it, and that the <hi>Pope</hi> by his <hi>Breve</hi> had con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned it, exhorting the <hi>Cathelikes of England</hi> to all Chriſtian patience and obedience. As for any other authority or ſuperiority of the <hi>Pope,</hi> then ſuch as is ſpirituall and neceſſary, for the unity of the <hi>Church,</hi> I have met with none that doe ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on it.</p>
                  <p>14. So that, whereas my hope was, that by find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out the corruptions of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> I ſhould grow farther in love with the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> and joyfully return home: and by inveighing againſt the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> both enjoy my preſent prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, and obtaine more and more; I ſaw the mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter was like to fall out cleane contrary. It is true indeed that there are many corruptions in all States; God hath no wheat-field in this world, wherein the Devill hath not tares growing; and there are no tares more rank then thoſe that grow among the wheat; For, <hi>optimi corruptio peſſima;</hi> and where grace abounds, if it be contemned, there ſin a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bounds much more. But ſeeing both my reading and experience hath now taught me, that the truth of <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> now taught and practiſed at this day in the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and all the obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent Members thereof, is the very ſame in ſubſtance, which was prefigured and propheſied from the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the world, perfected by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelf, delivered to his <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> and by them and their Succeſſors perpetually and univerſally in one uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formity practiced untill this day, without any ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiall alteration. And that the new <hi>Religion of England,</hi> wherein it doth differ, hath no ground,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97574:26"/> but either the pleaſure of the <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> or the common cry and voice of the People, nor no conſtancy or agreement with it ſelfe, what ſhould I now do? It is not in my power not to know that which I do know, nor to doubt of that which I have ſpent ſo much time, and taken ſo much paines, and beſtowed ſo much coſt, and made ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny trialls to find. And yet I know, if I ſhould yeeld to be reconciled to the <hi>Church,</hi> I ſhould be for this world in all likelihood, utterly undone; and that which grieved me more, I ſhould be rejected of <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> my moſt redoubted Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and deſpiſed by all my deare friends and lovers in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>15. Theſe were in my thoughts at the <hi>Spa,</hi> which did ſo vex and afflict my ſoule, as that the waters could do my body no good at all, but rather much hurt. Nevertheleſſe I avoided the company of <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> abſtained from the <hi>Church,</hi> and did both diſpute and write againſt the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as occaſion was offered. I ſtill hoped that time would give me better counſell, and therefore reſolved to go from the <hi>Spa</hi> to <hi>Heidelberg</hi> to do my duty there. In the meane time I thought with my ſelf, it may be God hath moved His <hi>Majeſties</hi> heart to think of peace and reconciliation. I know his diſpoſition was ſo in the beginning; and I remember <hi>M. Cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſabon</hi> told me when I brought him out of <hi>France,</hi> that his Errand was nothing elſe, but to medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate peace betwixt the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and the <hi>Church of England.</hi> Therefore I thought, before I would ſubmit my ſelfe to the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> I would write to <hi>M. Cauſabon</hi> ſuch a Letter as hee might ſhew unto <hi>your Mdjeſty,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining ſuch conditions as (I thought) might
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97574:27"/> ſatisfie <hi>your Majeſty</hi> if they were performed by the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> The copie of which Letter is too long here to ſet downe. But when Mr. <hi>Cauſabon</hi> an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered me that he knew <hi>your Majeſty</hi> was reſolved to have no ſociety with the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> upon any condition whatſoever, and that it would be my undoing, if thoſe my Letters ſhould come to <hi>your Majeſties</hi> hands, or of thoſe that bare the ſway, I began to deſpaire of my returne into <hi>England,</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe I would overthrow both the health of my bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy and the quiet of my mind, and either utterly damne my own ſoule, or greatly indanger not only my living and credit, but my life it ſelfe alſo, by reaſon of <hi>your Majeſties</hi> diſpleaſure, and the ſeveri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of the <hi>Statutes</hi> made, and in force againſt <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholikes,</hi> and <hi>Catholike Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>16. There is a <hi>Statute</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> made by <hi>King Henry,</hi> the 8. to make him ſupreme head of the <hi>Church</hi> in ſpirituall and Eccleſiaſticall Cauſes, which <hi>Statute</hi> injoynes all the Subjects of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> on paine of death, to believe and to ſweare they do believe that it is true. And yet all the world knowes, if <hi>King Henry</hi> the 8. could have gotten the <hi>Pope</hi> to divorce <hi>Q. Katherine,</hi> that he might marry <hi>Anne Boleigne,</hi> that Statute had never been made by him, and if that Title had not enabled the King to pull down <hi>Abbeyes</hi> and <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> and give them to Lay-men, the Lords and Commons of that time would never have ſuffered ſuch a Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tute to be made. This Statute was continued by <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> to ſerve her own turne, and it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firmed by <hi>your Majeſty</hi> to ſatisfie other men. And yet <hi>your Majeſty</hi> yeelds the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> to be the <hi>Mother Church,</hi> and the <hi>Biſhop of Rome</hi> to be the chiefe <hi>Biſhop</hi> or <hi>Primate</hi> of all the <hi>Weſterne</hi>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:97574:27"/> 
                     <hi>Churches,</hi> which I doe alſo verily believe, and therefore I do verily thinke he hath, or ought to have ſome ſpirituall Juriſdiction in <hi>England.</hi> And although in my younger daies, the faſhion of the world made me ſwear, as other men did (for which I pray God forgive me) yet I ever doubted, and am now reſolved that no Chriſtian man can take that <note n="*" place="margin">.i. Of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>premacy.</note> Oath with a ſafe conſcience, neither will I ever take it, to gaine the greateſt preferment in the world.</p>
                  <p>17. There is another <hi>Statute</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> made by <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> and confirmed by <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> which makes it death for any Engliſhman to be in <hi>England,</hi> being made a <hi>Prieſt</hi> by authority deri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, or pretended to be derived from the <hi>Biſhop of Rome;</hi> I cannot believe that I am a Prieſt at all, unleſſe I be made by authority derived from <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory</hi> the great, from whence all the <hi>Biſhops in Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> have their being, if they have any being at all.</p>
                  <p>18. There is another <hi>Statute</hi> in like manner made and confirmed, that it is death to be reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led by a <hi>Catholike Prieſt</hi> to the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> I am perſwaded that the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is our <hi>Mother Church,</hi> and that no man in <hi>England</hi> can be ſaved, that continues wilfully out of the viſible unity of that <hi>Church,</hi> and therefore I cannot chuſe, but perſwade the people to be reconciled thereunto, if poſſibly they can.</p>
                  <p>19. There is another <hi>Statute</hi> in like manner, made and confirmed, that it is death to exhort the people of <hi>England</hi> to <hi>Catholike Romane Religion,</hi> I am perſwaded that the Religion preſcribed, and practiſed by the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> is the true <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion,</hi> which I will particularly juſtifie; and
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97574:28"/> make plaine from point to point, if God give time and oportunity, and therefore I cannot chuſe but perſwade the people thereunto.</p>
                  <p>It may be theſe are not all ſeverall <hi>Statutes,</hi> ſome of them may be members of the ſame, (for I have not my bookes about me to ſearch) but I am ſure all of them do make ſuch felonies and treaſons, as were the greateſt vertues of the <hi>Primitive Church,</hi> and ſuch as I muſt needs confeſſe my ſelfe, I cannot chuſe if I live in <hi>England,</hi> but indeavour to be guilty of, and then it were eaſie to find <hi>Puritanes</hi> e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough to make a <hi>Jury</hi> againſt me, and there would not want a <hi>Juſtice of Peace</hi> to give a ſentence, and when they had done, that which is worſe then the perſecution it ſelfe, they would all ſweare ſolemnly that <hi>Doctor Carier</hi> was not put to death for <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion,</hi> but for Felony and Treaſon. I have no hope of protection againſt the cruelty of thoſe Lawes, if your Majeſty be reſolved upon no condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions whatſoever, to have any ſociety at all, or communion with the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore whilſt the caſe ſo ſtands, I dare not returne home againe. But I cannot be altogether out of hope of better newes before I die, as long as I do believe that the <hi>Saints</hi> in heaven do rejoyce at the conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of a ſinner to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and do know that <hi>your Majeſty</hi> by your birth, hath ſo great an intereſt in the <hi>Saints</hi> of heaven, as you ſhall never ceaſe to have, untill you ceaſe to be the ſon of ſuch a mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as would rejoyce more then all the reſt for your converſion. Wherefore I aſſure my ſelfe that ſhe with all the reſt doe pray that <hi>your Majeſty</hi> before you die, may be <hi>Mili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tant</hi> in the <hi>Communion</hi> of that <hi>Church,</hi> wherein they are <hi>Triumphant.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="15" facs="tcp:97574:28"/>
                  <p> And in this hope I am gone before to joyne my prayers with theirs in the unity of the <hi>Catholike Church.</hi> And do humbly pray <hi>your Majeſty</hi> to pardon me for doing that which was not in my power to avoid; and to give me leave to live, where I hope ſhortly to die, unleſſe I may hope to do <hi>your Majeſty</hi> ſervice, and without the prejudice of any honeſt man in <hi>England,</hi> to ſee ſome unity be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and her mother the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> And now having declared the meanes of my converſion to <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> I will briefly alſo ſhew unto you <hi>the hopes I have to do your Majeſty no ill ſervice therein.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="chapter">
                  <head>CHAP. II. <hi>The hopes I have to doe</hi> your Majeſtie <hi>no ill ſervice in being</hi> Catholike.</head>
                  <p>MY firſt hope that <hi>your Majeſty</hi> will accept of that for the beſt ſervice I can do you, which doth moſt further the glory of our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour,</hi> and my own ſalvation. Indeed there are Kingdomes in the world, where the chiefe care of the Governor is, <hi>Non quàm bonis, ſed quàm ſubditis regnent:</hi> ſuch were the heathen Kingdoms which S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> deſcribes (in his 2. <hi>de Civit. Dei, cap.</hi> 20.) In ſuch Common-wealths the way to be good Subjects is not to be good men, but to ſerve the times and the turns of them that beare the ſway whatſoever they are. But if it be true, (as ſome holy &amp; learned Fathers teach) that in a well-ordered Government there is, <hi>cadem faelicitas unius hominis, ac totius civitaiis,</hi> then I am ſure that it muſt follow, that in a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth truly Chriſtian there is, <hi>eadem virtus boni</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97574:29"/> 
                     <hi>viri, ac boni Civis.</hi> And therefore being a <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter and Preacher of England,</hi> if I will rather ſerve <hi>your Majeſty</hi> then my ſelf, and rather procure the good of your Kingdome then my own prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I am bound in duty to reſpect and ſeek for thoſe things above all other, that may advance the honour of God, and the ſalvation of my own ſoule, and the ſoules of thoſe who do any way belong to my charge; and being ſufficiently reſolved, that nothing can more advance the honour of our <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour</hi> and the common ſalvation, then to be in the unity of his <hi>Church,</hi> I have done you the beſt ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice I could at home, by preaching peace and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciliation, and being not able for the malice of the times, to ſtand any longer in the breach at home, I think it ſafeſt in this laſt caſt to look to mine own game, and by my daily Prayers and dying, to doe <hi>your Majeſtie</hi> the ſame ſervice in the unity of the <hi>Church,</hi> which by my daily preaching and living, I did indeavour to do in the midſt of the <hi>Schiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>2. And though it be ſufficient for a man of my profeſſion, to reſpect only matters of heaven, and of another world, yet becauſe this world was made for that other, I have not regarded my owne e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, that I might reſpect <hi>your Majeſties</hi> therein, and after long and ſerious meditation, which <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> might moſt honour <hi>your Majeſty</hi> even in this world, I have conceived undoubted hope that there is no other <hi>Religion</hi> that can procure true honour and ſecurity to <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and your Poſterity in this world, but the true <hi>Catholike Romane Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> which is the very ſame, whereby all your glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Predeceſſors have been advanced and protected on earth, and are everlaſtingly bleſſed in heaven.</p>
                  <p>3. The firſt reaſon of my hope is, the promiſe of
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97574:29"/> God himſelfe to bleſſe and honour thoſe, that bleſſe his <hi>Church</hi> and honour him, and to <note n="*" place="margin">No queſtion but this will come home in the end to the Church-Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phaners of our times.</note> curſe and confound thoſe that curſe his <hi>Church,</hi> and diſhonour him, which he hath made good in all ages. There was never any Man, or City, or State, or Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pire ſo preſerved and advanced, as they that have preſerved the unity and advanced the proſperity of the <hi>Church of Chriſt;</hi> nor ever any been made more miſerable and inglorious, then they that have diſhonoured <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and made havock of his <hi>Church</hi> by Schiſm and Hereſie.</p>
                  <p>4. If I had leiſure and bookes, it were eaſie for me to inlarge this point with a long inumeration of particulars. But I think it needleſſe, becauſe I can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not call to mind any example to the contrary, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept it be the State of <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> or ſome one or two other, lately fallen from the unity of the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church,</hi> or the State of the great <hi>Turk,</hi> that doth ſtill perſecute the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> and yet continues in great glory in this world. But when I conſider of <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> I find in her many ſingu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larities; ſhe was a woman, and a Maiden Queen, which gave her manie advantages of admiration, ſhe was the laſt of her race, and needed not care what became of the world after her owne daies were en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded. She came upon the Remainders of Devotion and <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> which like a Bowle in his courſe, or an Arrow in his flight, would go on for a while by the force of the firſt mover, and ſhe had a practiſe of maintaining warres among her neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours (which became a woman well) that ſhe might be quiet at home. And whatſoever proſperity or
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97574:30"/> honour there was in her daies, or is yet remaining in <hi>England,</hi> I cannot but aſcribe to the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> and to <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> which was for many hundred yeares together, the firſt mover of that Government, and is ſtill in every ſetled Kingdome, and hath yet left the ſteps, and ſhadow thereof behind it, which in all likeli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hood cannot continue many yeares without a new ſupply from the fountain.</p>
                  <p>5. As for the honor and greatneſſe of the <hi>Turke,</hi> and other <hi>Infidells,</hi> as it reacheth no farther then this life, ſo it hath no beginning from above this world; and if we
<note place="margin">
                        <hi>In Luc.</hi> 4. <hi>&amp; alibi.</hi>
                     </note> may believe S. <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> thoſe honors are conferred rather by Gods permiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, then by his donation, being indeed ordained, and ordered by his providence, but for the ſins of the people, conferred by the Prince that rules in the ayre. It is true, the <hi>Turkiſh Empire</hi> hath now con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued a long time, but they have other principles of State to ſtand upon. The continuall Guard of 100000. Souldiers, whereof moſt of them know no parents, but the <hi>Emperor.</hi> The Tenure of all his Subjects, who hold all <hi>in capite ad voluntatem Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini,</hi> by the ſervice of the ſword, their injoyned ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, and reverence in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> and their facility in admitting other <hi>Religions,</hi> as well as their owne to the hope of ſalvation, and to tole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate them, ſo that they be good Subjects.</p>
                  <p>Theſe and ſuch like are principles of great im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portance to increaſe an Empire, and to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine a Temporall State. But there is no State in Chriſtendome that may indure theſe principles, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe they meane to turne <hi>Turks</hi> alſo, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though ſome be willing to do, yet they will neither
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97574:30"/> hold in <hi>Capite,</hi> nor hold their peace in <hi>Religion,</hi> nor ſuffer their <hi>King</hi> to have ſuch a guard about him, nor admit of <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> ſo much as the <hi>Turk</hi> doth.</p>
                  <p>6. It is moſt true, which I gladly write, and am ready, with all the honour I can of <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> to ſpeak, that I thinke there was never any <hi>Catholike King</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> that did in his time more im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace and favour the true bodie of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> then <hi>your Majeſty</hi> doth that ſhadow thereof, which is yet left, and my firm hope is, that this your deſire to honour our <hi>Bleſſed Saviour</hi> in the ſhadow of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> will move him to honour <hi>your Majeſty</hi> ſo much as not to ſuffer you to die out of the body of his true <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> and in the mean time to let you underſtand that all honour that is intended to him by <hi>Schiſme</hi> &amp; <hi>Hereſie</hi> doth redound to his great diſhonour, both in reſpect of his <hi>Reall,</hi> and of his <hi>Myſticall Body.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>7. For his <hi>Reall Bodie</hi> it is not as the <hi>Ubiquita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries</hi> would have it every where, as well without the <hi>Church</hi> as within, but only where himſelfe would have it, and hath ordained that it ſhould be, and that is onely amongſt his <hi>Apoſtles</hi> and <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi> and their Succeſſors in the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> to whom he delivered his <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and promiſed to continue with them untill the worlds end; So that though <hi>Chriſt</hi> be preſent in that <hi>Schiſme,</hi> by the power of his Deity, (for ſo he is preſent in hell alſo) yet by the grace of his humanity, (by participation of which grace onely there is hope of ſalvation) he is not preſent there at all, except it be in corners and priſons, and places of perſecution. And therefore whatſoever ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour is pretended to be done to <hi>Chriſt</hi> in <hi>Schiſme</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:97574:31"/> and <hi>Hereſie,</hi> is not done to him, but to his utter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies.</p>
                  <p>8. And for his <hi>myſticall Body,</hi> which is his <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Kingdome,</hi> there can be no greater di<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>honor done to <hi>Chriſt,</hi> then to maintain ſchiſme and diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion therein. What would <hi>your Majeſty</hi> think of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Subjects of yours, that ſhould go about to raiſe civill diſſention or warres in your Kingdome, and of thoſe that ſhould f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſter, and adhere unto ſuch men? It is the faſhion of all <hi>Rebells</hi> when they are in Armes, to <note n="*" place="margin">You know who have done ſo of late.</note> pretend the ſafety of the King, and the good of the Countrey; but pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend what they will, you cannot account ſuch men any better then <hi>Traytors.</hi> And ſhall we beleeve that our <hi>B. Saviour,</hi> the <hi>King of Kings,</hi> doth ſit in heaven, and either not ſee the practiſes of thoſe, that under colour of ſerving him with <hi>Reformation,</hi> do nothing elſe, but ſerve their owne turnes, and diſtract his <hi>Church,</hi> that is his Kingdome on earth, with ſedition? Or ſhall we think that he will not in time revenge his wrong? Verily he ſees it, and doth regard it, and will in time revenge it.</p>
                  <p>9. But I hope and pray, that he may not revenge it upon you, nor yours, but rather that he will ſhew, that your deſire to honour him, is accepted of him, and therefore will move you to honour your ſelfe, and your poſterity, with beſtowing the ſame your favour upon his <hi>Church</hi> in the unity thereof, which you do now beſtow in the <hi>Schiſme,</hi> and that he will reward both you and yours for the ſame, according to his promiſe, not only with everlaſting glory in heaven, but alſo with long continued temporall ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour and ſecurity in this world. And this is the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97574:31"/> firſt reaſon of my hope, grounded upon the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe of God.</p>
                  <p>The ſecond Reaſon of my hope, that <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> may be a great meanes of honour and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curity, to <hi>your Majeſties</hi> poſterity, is taken from the conſideration of your neighbours, the Kings and Princes of Chriſtendome; among whom there is no State ancient, and truly honourable, but only thoſe that are <hi>Catholike.</hi> The reaſon whereof I take to be, becauſe the Rules of <hi>Catholike Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> are eternall, univerſall, and conſtant unto them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and withall ſo conſonant unto Majeſtie and greatneſſe, as they have made and preſerved the <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Church</hi> moſt reverent and venerable throughout the world for theſe 1600. yeares, and thoſe Temporall States that have been conforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thereunto, have been alwaies moſt honourable, and ſo are like to continue, untill they hearken unto <hi>Schiſme.</hi> And as for thoſe that have rejected and oppoſed the Rules of <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> they have been driven in ſhort time to degenerate, and become either tyrannicall or popular; <hi>your Majeſtie,</hi> I know doth abhor Tyranny, but if <hi>Schiſme</hi> and <hi>Hereſie</hi> might have their full ſwing cover the Seas, the very ſhadow and Reliques of Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty in <hi>England,</hi> ſhould be utterly <note n="*" place="margin">God grant this prove not too true.</note> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced and turned into <hi>Helvetian,</hi> or <hi>Belgian</hi> popularity: For, they that make no conſcience to prophane the Majeſty of God and his Saints, in the <hi>Church,</hi> will, after they feel their ſtrength, make no bones to violate the Majeſty of the <hi>King,</hi> and his Children in the Common-wealth.</p>
                  <p>10. I know well that the <hi>Puritanes of England,</hi> the <hi>Huguenots of France,</hi> and the <hi>Gueſes of Germa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny,</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:97574:32"/> together with the reſt of the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> of all ſorts are a great faction of Chriſtendome, and they are glad to have the pretence of ſo great a Majeſty to be their chief, and of your poſterity to be their hope: but I cannot be perſwaded that they ever will or can joyne together to advance <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> or your Children farther then they may make a preſent gaine by you. They are <note n="*" place="margin">One may ſweare it.</note> not agreed of their own <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> nor of the principles of U<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niverſall and Eternall Truth, and how can they be conſtant in the rules of particular, and tranſitory honor? where there is <hi>Nullum Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipium ordinis,</hi> there can be <hi>Nullum Principium honoris;</hi> ſuch is their caſe, there is a voice of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſion among them, as well in matters of State as of Religion. Their power is great, but not to edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, but deſtruction. They joyne together only againſt good order, which they call the <hi>Common E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy,</hi> and if they can deſtroy that, they will in all likelihood turn their fury againſt themſelves, and like Devills torment, like Serpents devoure one an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other. In the meane time if they can make their <hi>Burgers, Princes,</hi> and turn old Kingdomes into new States, it is like enough they will do it, but that they will ever agree together to make any one Prince, King, or Emperour over them all, and yeeld due obedience unto him, further then either their gaine ſhall allure them, or his Sword ſhall com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell them, that I cannot perſwade my ſelfe to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve. And therefore I cannot hope that <hi>your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> or your poſterity can expect the like honour or ſecurity from them, which you might do from <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Princes,</hi> if you were joyned firmly to them in the unity of <hi>Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="23" facs="tcp:97574:32"/>
                  <p> 12. The third reaſon of my hope, that <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> ſhould be moſt available for the honour and ſecurity of <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and your children, is taken from the conſideration of your Subjects, which can be kept in obedience to God, and to their King by no other <hi>Religion,</hi> and leaſt of all by the <hi>Calviniſts;</hi> for if their principles be received once, and well drunk in, and digeſted by your Subjects, they will openly maintaine, that God hath as well predeſtinated men to be <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>Is not this now o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penly profeſſed, by thoſe who would have the King called to an account?</hi> &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>Traytors,</hi> as to be <hi>Kings,</hi> and he hath as well predeſtinated men to be <hi>Theeves,</hi> as to be <hi>Judges,</hi> and he hath as well prede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinated that men ſhould ſin, as that <hi>Christ</hi> ſhould die for ſin; which kind of diſputations, I know by my experience in the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey, are ordinary, among your Countrey <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> that take themſelves to be learned in the Scriptures, eſpecially when they are met in the Ale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houſe, and have found a weaker brother, whom they think ſit to be inſtructed in the profound my<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſteries. And howſoever they be not yet all ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pudent, as to hold theſe concluſions in plain termes, yet it is certain they all hold theſe principles of Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, from whence working heads of greater li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berty, do at their pleaſures draw theſe conſequences, in their lives, and practiſes. And is <note n="*" place="margin">It now ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears it is not.</note> this a <hi>Religion</hi> ſit to keep Subjects in obedience to their Soveraigns?</p>
                  <p>13. Here I know the great Maſters of <hi>Schiſme,</hi> will never leave objecting the horrible treaſon of certaine <hi>Catholikes</hi> againſt <hi>your Majesty,</hi> which if
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:97574:33"/> the Devill had not wrought to their hands, they had had little to ſay againſt <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore this day. But I humbly intreat that the fact of of ſome few men, may not be for ever objected a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the truth of a generall Rule. It is not the queſtion which <hi>Religion</hi> will make all your Subjects true, but which <hi>Religion</hi> is moſt like to make all true. It is certaine there be Traytors againſt God and man, of all <hi>Religions,</hi> and <hi>Catholikes</hi> as they are the beſt Subjects, ſo when they fall to it, they are the worſt Traytors. But if we will look upon examples, or conſider of reaſons, the <hi>Catholike</hi> is the only Religion, which as it doth duly ſubordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate Kings unto God, ſo doth it effectually bind Subjects to performe all lawfull obedience to their Kings, I will not repeat examples, becauſe the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient are tedious, and the preſent are odious. But if there can be but one King named in all the world, that did ever receive honour from <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts,</hi> farther then to be their <hi>Champion or Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctor,</hi> untill their turne were ſerved, then I may be content to believe that <hi>your Majestie,</hi> and your Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mily ſhall receive perpetuity from them. But if your <hi>Calviniſts</hi> do profeſſe to honor you, and all other <hi>Calviniſts</hi> do overthrow their Kings and Princes whereſoever they can prevaile, I can hardly believe that yours do <note n="*" place="margin">It appears ſo now.</note> mean any more good earneſt then the reſt. There is certainly ſome other mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter that they are content for a time to honour <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> it cannot be their <hi>Religion</hi> that ties them to it, for it doth not tie them to it ſelfe. There is no principle of any <hi>Religion,</hi> nor any Article of any Faith, which a <hi>Calviniſt</hi> wil not call in queſtion and either altogether deny, or expound after his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:97574:33"/> owne fancy, and if he be reſtrained, he cries out by and by, <hi>that he cannot have the liberty of his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience.</hi> And what bond of obedience can there be in ſuch <hi>Religion?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>14. It is commonly objected by States-men, that it is no matter what opinions men hold in matters of <hi>Religion,</hi> ſo that they be kept in awe by Juſtice, and by the Sword: Indeed for this world it were no matter at all for <hi>Religion,</hi> if it were poſſible with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out it to do Juſtice, and to keep men in awe by the Sword. In Military eſtates whileſt the Sword is in the hand, there is the leſſe need of <hi>Religion,</hi> and yet the greateſt and moſt Martiall States that ever were, have been willing to uſe the conſcience and reverence of ſome <hi>Religion</hi> or other, to prepare the Subjects to obedience. But in a peaceable Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, ſuch as all Chriſtian Kingdomes do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe to be, if the reines of Religion be let looſe, the Sword commonly is too weak, and comes too late, and will be like enough to give the day to the Rebell: and ſeeing the laſt and ſtrongeſt bond of Juſtice is an Oath which is a principall act of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and were but a mockery, if it were not for the puniſhment of hell, and the reward of heaven, it is unpoſſible to execute Juſtice without the help of Religion. And therefore the neglect and contempt of Religion hath ever been, and ever ſhall be the fore-runner of deſtruction in all ſetled States what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever.</p>
                  <p>15. The <hi>Devill</hi> that intends the deſtruction as well of bodies, as of ſoules, and of whole States, as of particular men, doth not commonly begin with mens bodies, and with matters of State, but being himſelf a ſpirit, and the Father of lies, he doth firſt inſinuate himſelf into mens underſtandings by
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:97574:34"/> falſe principles of <hi>Religion,</hi> whereunto he hath the more eaſie entrance, becauſe he hath perſwaded their Governours to believe that it is no great mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter what opinions men hold in matters of Religion, ſo that they look well into their actions, and keep them in obedience, which perſwaſion is all one, as if the Enemy that beſiegeth a City, ſhould perſwade the Garriſon, that they might ſurrender the Caſtle unto him well enough, and keep the baſe Towne, and all the people of the Towne to themſelves. But when the divell hath prevailed ſo far, as by falſe opinions in matters of the firſt truth, that is of Religion, to get the underſtanding in poſſeſſion, which is the Caſtle as it were, and watch-tower both of the ſoule, and body, and ſtate, and all, he will peradventure diſſemble his purpoſe for a while, and by ſlandering of the truth and pleaſing them with the trifles of the world, (which by Gods permiſſion are in his power) make men believe, that the world is amended; for, <hi>Nemo repentè ſit peſſimus,</hi> but ſhortly after when he ſees his time, he will out of his <hi>Arſenal</hi> of falſe apprehenſions in under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, ſend forth ſuch diſtorted Engines of life and action, as will eaſily ſubdue both body, and goods, and ſtates, and all, to his devotion,</p>
                  <p>16. The <hi>Calvinisticall Preacher,</hi> when he hath gotten his honeſt, abuſed, and miſguided flock about him, will cry out againſt me for this <hi>Popiſh collecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> and call God and them to witneſſe, that he doth daily in his <hi>Sermons</hi> exhort men to good works, and to obedience unto the <hi>Kings Majeſty;</hi> and am not I and my brethren (ſaith he) and our flock, as honeſt, and as civill men, as any <hi>Papiſt</hi> of them all? For my own part I will not accuſe any <hi>Calviniſt</hi> though I could, neither
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:97574:34"/> can I excuſe all <hi>Papists,</hi> though I would.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Iliacos intra muros peccator &amp; extra.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But I muſt never forget that moſt true &amp; wiſe obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation which the noble &amp; learned Sir <hi>Francis Bacon</hi> makes in one of his firſt <hi>Eſſaies,</hi> viz. <hi>That all Schiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maticks utterly failing in the Precepts of the firſt Table concerning the Religion and worſhip of God, have neceſſity in policie to make a good ſhew of the ſecond Table, by their civill &amp; demure converſation towards men.</hi> For otherwiſe they ſhould at the firſt appeare, as afterwards they ſhew themſelves, to be altogether out of their ten Commandements; and ſo men would be as much aſhamed to follow them at the firſt, as they are at the laſt. It is a ſure rule of Policie, that in every mutation of State, the Authors of the Change, will for a while ſhew themſelves, or pretend to be honeſt, rather of ſpite, then of conſcience, that they may diſgrace thoſe, whom they have ſuppreſſed: but it doth never hold in the next generation. You ſhall ſcarce heare of a <hi>Puritan father,</hi> but his ſon proves either a <hi>Catholike</hi> or an <hi>Atheist:</hi> Muti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous Souldiers whileſt the Enemy is in the field, will be orderly, nor for love of their Generall, but for feare of the Enemie: but if they be not held in the ancient Diſcipline of Warrs, they will upon the leaſt truce or ceſlation, quickly ſhew them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
                  <p>17. And as for their exhortations to obedience to <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> when they have firſt infected the underſtanding of your Subjects, with ſuch principles of <hi>Rebellion,</hi> as have diſturbed and overthrown all other States, where they had their will, it is a ridiculous thing to think upon ſuch exhortati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and all one, as if a phantaſticall fellow,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:97574:35"/> finding a herd of young Cattell in a cloſe, ſhould firſt break downe the hedges, and then cry loud to the Cattell, not to venture to go out, nor to ſeek a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny fatter paſture, for fear they be put into the pound, and if they chance to feed where they are, becauſe they have no experience of other, and to tarry in the Cloſe for an houre or two, then the unhappy fellow ſhould run to the owner of the Cattell, and tell him what great ſervice he had done him, and how he had kept his Cattell in the Cloſe by his goodly charmes and exhortations. Let them ſay what they liſt of their own honeſty, and of their exhortations to obedience, as long as they do free<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly infect the peoples ſoules with ſuch falſe opinions in <hi>Religion,</hi> they do certainly ſow the ſeeds of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience, and <hi>Rebellion</hi> in mens underſtandings, which if they be not prevented by <hi>your Majesties</hi> gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving way to <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> will in all like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lihood ſpring up in the <note place="margin">K. Charles <hi>feels the ſad effects of this predictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi>
                     </note> next generation, to the great prejudice, and mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſtation of <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and your poſterity. So that whether I doe reſpect heaven, or earth, my own ſoule, or the ſervice of <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> God, or your Neighbours, or your Subjects, my aſſured hope is, that by joyning my ſelfe to the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> I neither have done, nor ever ſhall do any ill duty or ſervice unto <hi>your Majeſty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>18. But perhaps there is ſuch oppoſition both in matter of Doctrine, and in matter of State, as it is unpoſſible that ever there ſhould be any reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation at all betwixt the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> of which I humbly pray <hi>your Majesty</hi> to give me leave to ſhew you what I have ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerved.</p>
                  <pb n="29" facs="tcp:97574:35"/>
                  <p> 19. It is true, the breach hath continued now theſe many yeares, and it is much increaſed by ſo long continuance, ſo that it was never greater, then it ſeems to be at this day, nor ever more dangerous to deal withall; For if a man do but go about to ſtop it, there ariſeth preſently a great and fearfull noiſe, and roaring of the waters againſt him: but yet nevertheleſſe the greatneſſe of the noiſe ought not to diſcourage us, but rather to give us hope, that although it be wide, yet it is but ſhallow, and not far from the bottome, as proceeding from affection, which is ſudden and violent, and not from judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is quiet, conſtant, and alwaies like it ſelf; for if a man ask in cold blood, whether a <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Catholike</hi> may be ſaved, the moſt learned Church-man will not deny it. And if a man aske, whether a <hi>Romane Catholike</hi> may be a good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, the moſt wiſe States-man will eaſily grant it; May we be both ſaved? then we are not divided in God. May we be both good Subjects? then we are not divided in the King. What reaſon is there then that we ſhould be thus hotly and unplacably di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided?</p>
                  <p>20. Truly there is no reaſon at all, but only the violence of affection, which being in a courſe, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not without ſome force be ſtaied. The multitude doth ſeldome or never judge according to truth, but according to cuſtomes; and therefore having of purpoſe been bred, and brought up in the hatred of <hi>Spaniards</hi> and <hi>Papists,</hi> cannot chuſe but think they are bound to hate them ſtill; and that whoſoever ſpeaks a word in favour of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> or of <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> is their utter enemy. And the <hi>Puritannicall Preacher,</hi> who can have no being in charity, doth never ceaſe by falſifications, and
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:97574:36"/> ſlanders, to blow the coales, that he may burn them, and warm himſelfe.</p>
                  <p>But if <hi>your Majeſty</hi> ſhall ever bee pleaſed to command thoſe make bates to hold their peace a while, and to ſay nothing, but what they are able to prove by ſufficient authority, before thoſe who are able to judge, and in the mean time to admit a conference of learned and moderate men on either ſide, the people who are now abuſed, and with the light of the Goſpell held in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treme ignorance, are not yet ſo uncapable, but they will be glad to heare of the truth, when it ſhall be ſimply and evidently delivered by honeſt men; and then they will plainly ſee, that their <hi>Light</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> which they ſo much talk of, is but a counterfeit light in a <hi>Theeves lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tern,</hi> whereby honeſt mens eyes are dazzled, and their Purſes robbed. And it will alſo appear that there is not indeed any ſuch irreconcile<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able oppoſition betwixt the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as they that live by the <hi>Schiſme,</hi> do make the world believe there is, neither in matter of Doctrine, nor matter of State.</p>
                  <p>21. For matter of Doctrine there is no reaſon that <hi>your Majeſty</hi> or the Kingdome ſhould be mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſted, or burdened for the maintenance of <hi>Calvi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſme,</hi> which is as much <note n="*" place="margin">Indeed a true Proteſtant and a Papiſt are now almoſt e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually odious.</note> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Religion of England,</hi> as it is againſt the <hi>Religion of Rome,</hi> and will by neceſſary conſequence overthrow not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> the <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> and the <hi>forgiveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> but alſo all the Articles of
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:97574:36"/> the <hi>Creed,</hi> ſaving only ſo much as the <hi>Turk</hi> himſelfe will be content to believe, which will be eaſie to prove upon better leiſure.</p>
                  <p>The Doctrine of <hi>England</hi> is that which is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the <hi>Common Prayer Book</hi> and <hi>Church Catechiſme</hi> confirmed by Act of <hi>Parliament,</hi> and by your <hi>Majeſties Edict,</hi> wherein all Engliſh men are Baptized, and ought to be confirmed, and therefore there is ſome reaſon that this ſhould be ſtood upon.</p>
                  <p>But this Doctrine, in moſt of the main points thereof (as hath been touched before, and requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth a juſt treatiſe to ſet down in particular,) doth much differ from the current opinions and Catechiſmes of <hi>Calviniſme,</hi> or doth very neer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree with, or at leaſt not contradict the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> if we liſt with patience to hear one another. And thoſe points of Doctrine wherein we are made to be at warrs with the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> whether we will or not, do rather argue the Corruptions of that ſtate, from whence they come, then are argued by the grounds of that <hi>Religion</hi> whereupon they ſtand; and the contradiction of Doctrine hath followed the altera<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ion of State, and not the alteration of State been grounded upon any truth of Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>22. For when the breach was reſolved upon for the perſonall and particular eaſe of <hi>King Hen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry the eight,</hi> and the Children of his later Wives, it was neceſſary to give every part of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth contentment, for which they might hold out in the heat of affection, and ſtudy to main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain the breach, otherwiſe it was likely that in the clearneſſe of Judgement it would quickly have grown together again, and then the Authors thereof
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:97574:37"/> muſt have been excluded, and given account of their practiſe.</p>
                  <p>23. Therefore to the <hi>Lords</hi> and <note n="*" place="margin">In like manner the Members of Parliament, and their Adherents have now purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the Biſhops Lands at eaſie rates, &amp;c.</note> 
                     <hi>Favourites</hi> of the Court were given the Lands and Inheritance of the <hi>Ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beys,</hi> and <hi>religious Houſes,</hi> that having once as it were, waſhed their hands in the bowells and blood of the <hi>Church,</hi> both they and their poſterity might be at utter de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiance therewith. And ſo having overthrowne and prophaned the good works of the <hi>Saints,</hi> it was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary for them to get them <hi>Chaplains</hi> that might both diſpute, preach and write againſt the merits of <hi>good works,</hi> the <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> the <hi>ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice of the Altar, Prayer for the dead,</hi> and all ſuch points of <hi>Catholike Doctrine,</hi> as were the grounds of thoſe <hi>Churches</hi> and <hi>Religious Houſes,</hi> which they had overthrowne and prophaned. And it was not hard for thoſe <hi>Chaplains</hi> by ſome ſhew of Scripture to prove that which their Lords and their followers were ſo willing to believe.</p>
                  <p>24. To the <hi>Commons</hi> was given great hope of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe for their poverty, caſe of Subſidies, and of the burden of ſo great a <hi>Clergie,</hi> and many other good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gay nothings. And for the preſent they ſhould have liberty, and the benefit of the <hi>Common-Law,</hi> that is, leave to live by ſuch Lawes as themſelves liſt to make, and to contemne the Authority of the <hi>Church,</hi> which although it were for their benefit e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very way, yet becauſe it croſſed their affections, like wayward Children, they could never abide it. And was not this reaſon enough for them to hold out
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:97574:37"/> the breach, and to ſtudy Scripture themſelves, that they might be able to confute <hi>Confeſſion, Satisfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Penance,</hi> and to declaime againſt all that Tyranny of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> whereby them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and their fore-fathers had been kept in awe and obedience unto God, and their Kings?</p>
                  <p>25. To the <hi>Clergy</hi> men that would turne with the times, beſides the poſſibility of preſent prefer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment by the alteration, was given ſhortly after leave to marry, and to purchaſe, and injoy the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit and pleaſure of the world, as well as the Laity. And what carnall minded <hi>Monk,</hi> or <hi>Prieſt,</hi> would not with might and maine keep open the breach, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he was once plunged in it, rather then be in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to forgo ſo pleaſing a commodity? Hence did ariſe a neceſſity of ſpeaking, and writing againſt <hi>Vowes, Virginity, Poverty, Fasting, Praying, Watching, Obedience,</hi> and all that auſterity of life, which is by the Lawes of the <hi>Church</hi> required in a Monaſticall, and Prieſtly Converſation.</p>
                  <p>26. Upon theſe conditions, the <hi>Lords,</hi> the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons,</hi> and the <hi>Clergie,</hi> were content to believe that <hi>the King was ſupreme Head of the Church of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> not that they did think ſo indeed, or that they deſired to augment his authority, but that they might be protected by him, and freely injoy thoſe commodities,
<note place="margin">So our Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers love not to hear of peace or unity, leſt they ſhould come to loſe their ſo eaſie bought Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhops lands, &amp; other profits.</note> which they thought <hi>Schiſme</hi> had brought unto them, and feared the unity of the <hi>Church</hi> might again take from them. Hence did ariſe a neceſſity of inveigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing againſt the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as againſt <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt</hi> and <hi>Babylon,</hi> and the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:97574:38"/> greateſt enemies of the State of <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Inſomuch that that Clergie-man was moſt accep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table to them, and in their opinion moſt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy of preferments, that could moſt confidently preach, and write the moſt foule, and monſtrous aſſertions of the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> though they were never ſo falſe. Theſe and ſuch like are thoſe temporall reſpects, which would faine ſeem the daughters of thoſe Doctrines, which themſelves have brought forth, and to be divided from the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> by Doctrine, when they themſelves have cauſed the Doctrine of Diviſion.</p>
                  <p>27. In all theſe, and all other Doctrines of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion, men have received great countenance, and incouragement from <hi>Geneva;</hi> For although <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. <hi>John Calvin</hi> were never any good Subject, or friend to <hi>Biſhop, Duke,</hi> or <hi>King,</hi> yet he did ſo fit the common people with new Doctrine, that no <hi>Goſpell</hi> can be ſo pleaſing to them, nor ſo light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome as his. For finding <hi>Geneva</hi> to be fallen out both with their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> (who was their anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent <hi>Prince)</hi> and their <hi>Duke,</hi> to whom they pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended againſt their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and to be all in a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſtion among themſelves for want of government, although he were then a ſtranger, and a very young man of ſome 26. or 27. years old at the moſt, yet he thought good upon the oportunity to give the ven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and to ſtep in himſelfe to be the founder of a new Church, and State amongſt them, and for that purpoſe, he found them out ſuch a <hi>Catechiſme,</hi> as they might eaſily contemn all ancient Learning and authority, and ſave themſelves by a ſtrong fan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, which he called <hi>Faith.</hi> And this pleaſed the <hi>Burgers</hi> of <hi>Geneva</hi> ſo well, that they called a mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:97574:38"/> and cauſed all the Citizens to ſweare, that that <hi>Catechiſme</hi> was true, and that all <hi>Popery</hi> was falſe, as may appeare in <hi>Calvins</hi> life, written by <hi>Beza</hi> himſelfe, and prefixed to his <hi>Epiſtles.</hi> And although the <hi>Miniſteriall Presbytery</hi> of <hi>Geneva,</hi> hath loſt much of M. <hi>Calvins</hi> greatneſſe, yet the <hi>Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty</hi> hath had the fortune ever ſince by the help of their neighbours to hold out againſt their <hi>Biſhop,</hi> and their <hi>Duke,</hi> and all their ancient Governours.</p>
                  <p>28. Now it is the nature of all common peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, eſpecially of Iſlanders, not only ſtill to
<note n="*" place="margin">Theſe late times witneſſe this truth ſuffi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciently.</note> affect more and more novelty and liberty, and to be wearie of their old Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie, but alſo to admire any thing that comes from beyond the Seas, &amp; to cheriſh, and comfort one another with reporting the good ſucceſſe which <hi>Schiſmaticks</hi> and <hi>Rebells</hi> happen to have againſt their lawfull Prelates and ancient Governours, &amp; to impute all their good fortune to their new <hi>Religion.</hi> Hence it comes to paſſe, that that Doctrine, which is indeed the lawfull Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> is neglected, and contemned as a Relique, or a <hi>Rag of Popery,</hi> and <hi>Calvins Inſtitutions</hi> being come from <hi>Geneva,</hi> and fairly bound up with the <hi>Preface</hi> of the <hi>Goſpell,</hi> is diſperſed throughout all <hi>Schooles, Cities, and Villages of England,</hi> and hath ſo infected both <hi>Prieſt</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> as although it be againſt Law, yet it is cried up by voices to be the only current Divinity in Court, and Countrey. In hope (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like) that it may one day ſerve the turn in <hi>England,</hi> as well as it hath done in <hi>Geneva,</hi> and in other pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where it hath prevailed.</p>
                  <p>28. Theſe reaſons, or rather Corruptions of State,
<pb facs="tcp:97574:39"/> have ſo confounded the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and ſo ſlandered the Doctrine of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> as it hath turned mens braines, and made the multitude on both ſides like two fools, who being ſet back to back, do think they are as far aſunder as the <hi>Horizons</hi> are, which they look upon. But if it might pleaſe <hi>your Majesty</hi> to command them to turne but each of them a quarter about, and looke both one way to the Service of God, and <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and to the ſalvation of ſoules, they ſhould preſently ſee themſelves to be a great deale more neer together in matters of Doctrine, then the <hi>Puritannicall Preachers</hi> on both ſides doe make them believe they are. I cannot in the brevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of this diſcourſe deſcend into particulars, but if it pleaſe <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> to command me, or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther honeſt man, that hath taken paines to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, and obſerve all ſides freely, and plainely to ſet downe the difference betwixt <hi>Calviniſme,</hi> and the Doctrine of <hi>England</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law, and and then to ſhew <hi>Locos conceſſos,</hi> and <hi>Locos contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſos,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Church of England,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> I doubt not but the diſtance that will be left betwixt, for matter of Doctrine, may by <hi>your Majestie,</hi> be eaſily compounded.</p>
                  <p>30. But perhaps there is ſo great oppoſition in matter of State, that although the Doctrine might be compounded, yet it is unpoſſible to heare of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement. And if there be the ſame reaſon of State which there was in the beginning, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinued all <hi>Q. Elizabeths</hi> daies, there is as little hope now that <hi>your Majeſtie</hi> ſhould hearken to reconcilia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, as there was that <hi>King Henry</hi> 8. or <hi>Q. Elizabeth</hi> would. But when I doe, with the greateſt reſpect I can, conſider the State of <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> your <hi>Lords,</hi>
                     <pb n="37" facs="tcp:97574:39"/> your <hi>Commons,</hi> and your <hi>Clergie,</hi> I do find as little cauſe of holding out, in reaſon of State, as I do in truth of Doctrine.</p>
                  <p>31. <hi>King Henry</hi> the 8. (although he had written that book againſt the Schiſme of <hi>Luther,</hi> in the defence of the <hi>Sea Apoſtolike,</hi> for which he deſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Title of <hi>Defenſor Fidei,</hi> yet) when he gave way to the luſt of <hi>Anne Bolen,</hi> and the flattery of his Favourites, and ſaw he could not otherwiſe have his will, he excluded the <hi>Pope,</hi> and made him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe <hi>ſupreme Head of the Church,</hi> that ſo he might not only diſpenſe with himſelfe for his luſt, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo ſupply his exceſſe with the ſpoile of the <hi>Church,</hi> which was then very rich. But when he ſaw God bleſſed him not, neither in his wiving, nor in his thriving, he was weary of his Supremacy before he died, and wiſhed himſelfe in the <hi>Church</hi> again, but he died in the Curſe of his Father, whoſe foundati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions he overthrew, and hath neither child to honour him, nor ſo much as a <hi>Tomb</hi> upon his grave to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member him, which ſome men take to be a token of the Curſe of God.</p>
                  <p>32. <hi>Q. Elizabeth,</hi> although ſhe were the daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of Schiſme, yet at her firſt coming to the <hi>Crown,</hi> ſhe would have the <hi>Common-Prayer Booke,</hi> and <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme,</hi> ſo ſet down, that ſhe might both by <hi>Engliſh ſervice,</hi> ſatisfie the <hi>Commons,</hi> who were greedy of alteration, and by <hi>Catholike opinions</hi> give hope to her Neighbour Princes, that ſhe would her ſelfe continue <hi>Catholike.</hi> And all her life long ſhe carri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed her ſelfe ſo betwixt the <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and the <hi>Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viniſts,</hi> as ſhe kept them both ſtill in hope. Yet being the daughter of the breach-maker, and having both her <hi>Crowne,</hi> and her life from the <hi>Schiſme,</hi> it was both diſhonourable, and dangerous for her
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:97574:40"/> to hearken to reconcilement. And therefore after ſhe was provoked by the excommunication of <hi>Pius Quintus,</hi> ſhe did ſuffer ſuch Laws to be made by her <hi>Parliaments,</hi> as might cry quittance with the <hi>Pope,</hi> and the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> And this courſe ſeemed in policy neceſſary for her, who was the daughter of <hi>King Henry the</hi> 8. by <hi>Anne Bolen,</hi> born with the contempt of <hi>Rome,</hi> the diſgrace of <hi>Spaine,</hi> and the prejudice of <hi>Scotland.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>33. But now that <hi>your Majesty</hi> is by the conſent of all ſides come to the Crown, and your undoubted Title ſetled with long poſſeſſion, the caſe is very much altered, for <hi>your Majeſty</hi> hath no need of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penſations, nor no will to pull down <hi>Churches,</hi> nor no dependence at all on <hi>Henry the</hi> 8. and if this Schiſme could have prevented your Title with the divorce of one wife, and the marrying of five more, neither your Mother nor your ſelf, ſhould ever have made Q. <hi>Elizabeth</hi> afraid with your right to the Crown of <hi>England.</hi> And therefore although it were neceſſary in reaſon of State to continue the Doctrine of diviſion, as long as the fruit of that Doctrine did continue, yet now the fruit of Schiſm is all ſpent, and that <hi>Parenthefis of State</hi> is at an end, there is no reaſon, but that the old ſentence may return againe, and be continued in that ſenſe, as if the <hi>Parentheſis</hi> had been clean left out; and that God had of purpoſe croſſed the fleſhly pretence of Schiſme, and raiſed <hi>your Majeſty</hi> to reſtore it, as your moſt wiſe, and Catholike Progenitor <hi>King Henry</hi> the 7. did leave it.</p>
                  <p>34. But perhaps the <hi>Schiſme</hi> though it ſerve you to no uſe at all for your Title, yet it doth much in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe your authority and your wealth, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore it cannot ſtand with your honour to farther the unity of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="39" facs="tcp:97574:40"/>
                  <p> Truly thoſe your moſt famous and renowned <hi>Anceſtors,</hi> that did part with their authority, and their wealth to beſtow them upon the <hi>Church of Christ,</hi> and did curſe and execrate thoſe that ſhould diminiſh them, and take them away againe, did not think ſo, nor find it ſo: and I would to God <hi>your Majeſty</hi> were ſo powerfull, and ſo rich, as ſome of thoſe <hi>Kings</hi> were, that were moſt bountifull that way. You are our Soveraigne Lord, all our bodies, and our goods are at your command, but our ſouls, as they belong not to your charge, but by way of protection in <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> ſo they cannot increaſe your honour or authority, but in a due ſubordination unto <hi>Chriſt,</hi> and to thoſe that ſupply his place in <hi>iis quae ſunt Juris divini.</hi> It was eſſentiall to heathen <hi>Emperors</hi> to be <hi>Pontifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces,</hi> as well as <hi>Reges,</hi> becauſe they were themſelves Authors of their owne <hi>Religion.</hi> But among <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,</hi> where <hi>Religion</hi> comes from <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who was no worldly <hi>Emperor</hi> (though above them all,) the Spirituall and Temporall Authority, have two beginnings, and therefore two ſupremes, who if they be ſubordinate, doe uphold and increaſe one another; but if the temporall authority doe oppoſe the ſpirituall, it deſtroyes it ſelfe, and diſhonours him from whom the ſpirituall authority is derived. <hi>Hereſie</hi> doth naturally ſpread it ſelf, like a <hi>Canker,</hi> and needs little help to put it forward; So that it is an eaſie matter for a mean Prince to bee a great man amongſt <hi>Heretikes,</hi> but it is an hard matter for a great King to <note n="*" place="margin">
                        <hi>K.</hi> Cha. <hi>knows this to be true by wofull experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence.</hi>
                     </note> govern them. When I have ſomtimes obſerved, how hard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>your Majeſty</hi> could effect your moſt unreaſonable deſires
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:97574:41"/> amongſt thoſe that ſtand moſt upon your Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy, I have been bold to be angrie, but durſt ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, only I did with my ſelfe reſolve for certaine, that the <hi>Keyes</hi> were wont to do the <hi>Crowne</hi> more ſervice, when they were in the <hi>Armes</hi> of the <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>er,</hi> then they can do, now they are tied together with the <hi>Scepter,</hi> and that your Title in ſpirituall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faires doth but ſerve other mens turnes, and not your own.</p>
                  <p>35. As for your wealth, it is true, that the <hi>Crown</hi> hath more pence paid unto it now, then in <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> times it had, but it hath never the more wealth. It is but the gain of the Tellers to have more mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, true wealth is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, he is the richeſt Prince, that hath meanes to main<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>ine the greateſt Army, &amp; to do moſt magnificent works both in war and peace, wherein the facts of your <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Anceſtors</hi> do appeare upon good Record, <hi>your Majeſties</hi> are but yet hoped for, and if ever you have the help of <hi>Catholike Religion</hi> to aſſiſt you, I hope you ſhall excell them all; otherwiſe I aſſure my ſelf, the <hi>Schiſme</hi> will do what it can to make you poore, and then complaine, that you are not rich. It was indeed one of the main pretences in the <hi>Statutes</hi> of <hi>Henry the</hi> 8. that the Schiſme might inrich the King, and maintain his wars, but God did not bleſſe it; for notwithſtanding
<note place="margin">No more will Church-lands inrich this Parliament, or the Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſers.</note> all the <hi>Church-lands,</hi> and <hi>Goods,</hi> and <hi>Tenths,</hi> and <hi>Fruits,</hi> and <hi>Praemunires, King Henry the</hi> 8. was faine to abaſe his coine more then once, and yet he died not ſo rich as his <hi>Catholike Father</hi> left him. And ſince his time what is become of the <hi>Court of Augmentation?</hi> what
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:97574:41"/> benefit you receive of all the <hi>Church-lands,</hi> more then your <hi>Progenitors</hi> did when they were in the hands of the <hi>Clergie,</hi> what caſe your Subjects have of <hi>Subſidies</hi> thereby, or in briefe, how much your Coffers are in iched, you may be pleaſed to be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſe that have to do with thoſe offices, and can readily give you an account: for mine own part I have diligently read over all the <hi>Statutes</hi> made by <hi>Henry the</hi> 8. and do find that the Events are ſo clean contrary to the Prefaces and pretences of them, as if God of purpoſe would laugh them to ſcorne.</p>
                  <p>36. There is yet another objection or two in reaſon of State concerning <hi>your Majeſtie,</hi> which ſeem to be harder to anſwer, then all the reſt, whereof the one is, that <hi>your Majeſtie</hi> hath under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken the cauſe in writing, and ſet out a booke in Print, and it muſt needs be great diſhonour to you to recall it. This indeed is that which I have heard the <hi>Calviniſts</hi> of <hi>England</hi> often wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h for, before it was done, and much boaſt of, after it was by means effected, that <hi>your Majeſtie</hi> ſhould be no longer a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to ſhew your ſelfe indifferent, as you did at the firſt, but were now ingaged upon your honour, to maintain their party, and to oppugne the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes,</hi> and altogether to ſuppreſſe them. But there is nothing in that book, why <hi>your Majeſty</hi> may not when you pleaſe admit the <hi>Popes Supremacy</hi> in ſpiritualls. And you are partly ingaged thereby to admit the triall of the firſt <hi>Generall Councells,</hi> and moſt <hi>Ancient Fathers.</hi> And as for the que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion of <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> it is but an <hi>Hypotheticall</hi> propoſition, and ſo reſerved, as you may recall your ſelf when you will; and howſoever that booke came forth either of your owne diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:97574:42"/> or by the daily inſtigation of ſome others, that did abuſe your Clemencie, and ſeek to ſend you of their own Errand, it cannot ſerve their turns, nor hinder <hi>your Majeſty</hi> from harkening to an end of contention. For if <hi>King Henry the</hi> 8. in the Judgement of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> might ſave his Honour, and contradict his Book from very good, to ſtark naught, they muſt not deny, but that <hi>your Majeſty</hi> may encreaſe your Honour by altering your Book from leſſe good, to much better.</p>
                  <p>37. The other and the greateſt objection, that howſoever <hi>your Majeſty</hi> before your coming to the <hi>Crowne,</hi> and in the beginning of your Raigne, were indifferent, yet after the <hi>Gunpowder Treaſon,</hi> you were ſo angred, and averted, as now you are reſolved never to be friends. And therefore he is no good Subject, that will either himſelfe be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled to the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> or perſwade any of your Subjects thereunto. It is true, I confeſſe, <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> had great cauſe to bee throughly angry, and ſo had all good men, whether <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likes</hi> or <hi>Proteſtants:</hi> but if <hi>your Majeſty</hi> will harken to thoſe, that work their own purpoſes out of your anger, you ſhall be driven to live and die out of Charity; which although it be not ſo horrible to the body, yet is it more harmfull to the ſoule, then violent or ſuddain death. It is hard I confeſſe for a private man to aſſwage his anger on the ſuddain, and there is as much difference betwixt the anger of a private man, and the indignation of a Prince, as betwixt a blaſt upon the River, which is ſoon down, and a ſtorme upon the Sea, which having raiſed the billowes to the height, is nouriſhed by the motion thereof, and cannot ſettle againe, in a long time. But
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:97574:42"/> there is a time for all things; And ſeven yeares is a long time. When a man is in the midſt of his anger, it pleaſeth him not to be intreated by his neighbours, much leſſe by his ſervants; but when a man hath chidden, and puniſhed untill he is weary, he will be content to heare his ſervant ſpeake rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon. And though he be not the wiſeſt, yet he is the lovingeſt ſervant that will venture to ſpeake to his Maſter in ſuch a caſe. God himſelf is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orable, and it pleaſeth him to be intreated by his Servants for his Enemies. I am perſwaded there is no good <hi>Catholike</hi> in the world, that can be <hi>your Majeſties</hi> Enemy. And therefore I doe aſſure my ſelfe, that God will be pleaſed with you to heare them ſpeake, and not angry with me for moving you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> thereunto. And if <hi>your Majeſty</hi> do but vouchſafe ſo much patience as to give equall hearing, I doubt not but you ſhall receive ſuch ſatisfaction, as will give you great quiet, and contentment, and diſquiet none of your Subjects, but thoſe only, that do for their advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage miſinforme <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and miſlead your people.</p>
                  <p>And if <hi>your Majeſty</hi> have no ſuch uſe of the Schiſme, as <hi>King Henry the</hi> 8. and <hi>Q. Elizabeth</hi> had, and that it doth neither increaſe your authori<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ty, nor your wealth, nor your honour, but rather hinder them all, and deprive you of that bleſſing which otherwiſe you might expect from <hi>Chriſt</hi> and his <hi>Church,</hi> from your <hi>Catholike neighbour Princes,</hi> and Subjects, and from the <hi>Saints</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> heaven, in whoſe communion is the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt comfort of every <hi>Christian,</hi> both in life and death, then whatſoever ſome great Stateſman may ſay to the contrary, I do verily believe they doe
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:97574:43"/> but ſpeak for themſelves, and that there is no true Reaſon, that may concern your <hi>Majeſty,</hi> to hinder you from admitting a toleration of <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> that thoſe who cannot com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand their underſtanding to think otherwiſe, may find the comfort, they do with ſo great zeale purſue, in the unity of the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> amongſt whom I confeſſe my ſelf to be one, that would think my ſelf the happieſt man in the world, if I might un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand that <hi>your Majeſty</hi> were content that I ſhould be ſo.</p>
                  <p>38. But although <hi>your Majeſty</hi> ſit at the ſterne, and command all, yet you are carried in the ſame ſhip; and it is not poſſible to weild ſo great a veſſell againſt wind and tide. And therefore although it do not concern <hi>your Majeſty</hi> in your own eſtate, yet if your <hi>Lords,</hi> and your <hi>Commons,</hi> and your <hi>Clergie</hi> do reap any great benefit by the <hi>Schiſme,</hi> it will be very hard for <hi>your Majeſty</hi> to effect unity. But if upon due examination there be no ſuch matter, then it is but the cry of the paſſengers, who, for want of experience, are afraid where there is no danger, and that can be no hinderance to any courſe <hi>your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſty</hi> ſhall think to be beſt, for the attaining of the haven.</p>
                  <p>39. For my own part, for the diſcharge of my duty, and conſcience, I have conſidered of all their ſtates, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nd can reſolve my ſelf, that I have not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiced the ſtate of any good Subject of yours, but mine own, in coming to the <hi>Catholike Church.</hi> And firſt for your <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Nobles.</hi> It is true that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of their <hi>Anceſtors</hi> were allowed a very good ſhare in the diviſion of the <hi>Church,</hi> when the Schiſm began, and therefore it concerned them in reaſon of their ſtate to maintaine the doctrine of diviſion. But
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:97574:43"/> I think there are very few in <hi>England,</hi> either <hi>Lords,</hi> or other now poſſeſt of <hi>Abbey lands,</hi> which have not paid well for them, and might not as well poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſe them in the unity of the <hi>Church;</hi> as in the <hi>Schiſme.</hi> And there was a Declaration made by the <hi>Pope</hi> to that purpoſe in <hi>Queen Maries</hi> dayes; ſo that there is now no need at all to preach againſt the merits of <hi>good works,</hi> nor the vertue of the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> nor the <hi>Invocation of Saints,</hi> nor the reſt of that <hi>Popery,</hi> that built <hi>Churches,</hi> unleſſe it be to help the <hi>Huguenots</hi> of <hi>France</hi> to pull them down.</p>
                  <p>40. But perhaps the <hi>Commons of England</hi> do gain ſo much by the <hi>Schiſme,</hi> as they cannot abide to heare of unity. Indeed when the <hi>Puritan Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cher</hi> hath called his flock about him, and deſcribed the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> to be ſo ignorant, ſo idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trous, and ſo wicked as he hath made himſelf believe ſhe is; then is he wont to congratulate his poor de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived Audience, that they, by the means of ſuch good men as himſelf is, are delivered from the dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, idolatry, and wickedneſſe of <hi>Popery,</hi> and there is no man dare ſay a word, or once mutter to the contrary. But the People have heard theſe lies ſo long, as moſt of them begin to be weary, and the wiſeſt of them cannot but wonder, how theſe <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritan Preachers</hi> ſhould become more learned, and more honeſt, then all the reſt that lived in anci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent times, or that live ſtill in <hi>Catholike Countries,</hi> or then thoſe in <hi>England,</hi> whom theſe men are wont to condemne for <hi>Papiſts.</hi> Nevertheleſſe I confeſſe there be many honeſt men and women amongſt them, that being carried away with prejudice and pretext of <hi>Scriptures,</hi> do follow theſe <hi>Preachers</hi> out of zeale and devotion to the truth, as my ſelfe did, untill I knew it was but counterfeit. And theſe
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:97574:44"/> good People, if they might be ſo happy as to heare <hi>Catholikes</hi> anſwer for themſelves, and tell them the truth, would be the moſt devout <hi>Catholikes</hi> of all other. But moſt of the People were never led by Sermons; if they were, the <hi>Catholike Church</hi> is both able, and willing to ſupply them far better then the <hi>Schiſme.</hi> But it was an opinion of wealth and liberty, which made them break at the firſt, and if they doe duly conſider of it, they are never the better for either of both, but much the worſe.</p>
                  <p>41. For wealth the <hi>Puritan unthrift,</hi> (that looks for the overthrow of Biſhops, and Churches Cathedrall) hopes to have his ſhare in them, if they would fall once; and therefore he cannot chuſe, but deſire to increaſe the Schiſme, that he may gain by it: but the honeſt <hi>Proteſtant</hi> that can en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dure the State of the <hi>Church of England</hi> as it is, could be content it were, as it was, for he ſhould re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive more benefit by it every way.</p>
                  <p>The poore <hi>Gentleman</hi> and <hi>Yeoman,</hi> that are burdened with many Children, may remember that in <hi>Catholike times,</hi> the <hi>Church</hi> would have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived and provided for many of their ſonnes and daughters, ſo as themſelves might have lived and died in the ſervice of God without poſterity, and have helped to maintain the reſt of their Families, which was ſo great a benefit to the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, both for the exoneration and proviſion thereof, as no humane policie can procure the like. The Farmer and Husbandman, who labors hard, to diſcharge his payments, and hath little or no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing left at the years end to lay up for his Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that increaſe and grow upon him, may re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member that in <hi>Catholike times</hi> there were better penny-worths to be had, when as the <hi>Clergie</hi> had a
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:97574:44"/> great part of the land in their hands, who had no need to raiſe their Rents themſelves, and did what they might to make other Lords let at a reaſonable rate, which was alſo an ineſtimable benefit to the <hi>Commons.</hi> So that whereas ignorant men carried with envy againſt the Clergie, are wont to object the multitude of them, and the greatneſſe of their proviſions, they ſpeak therein, as much againſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves as is poſſible. For the greater the number is of ſuch men as are <hi>Mundo mortui,</hi> the more is the exoneration of the <hi>Commons,</hi> and the more the lands are of ſuch, as can have no propriety in them, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is the proviſion of the <hi>Commons.</hi> For themſelves can have no more but their food, and regular appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rell, all the reſt either remaines in the hands of the Tenants, or returnes in Hoſpitality, and relief to their Neighbours, or is kept as in a living <hi>Exchequer,</hi> for the ſervice of Prince and Country in time of neceſſity. So that the <hi>Commons</hi> do gain no wealth at all, but rather loſe much by the <hi>Schiſme.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>42. And as for liberty, they are indeed freed from the poſſibility of going to <hi>ſhrift,</hi> that is of confeſſing their ſinnes to God, in the eare of a <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholike Prieſt,</hi> and receiving comfort and counſell againſt their ſinnes from God, by the mouth of the ſame <hi>Prieſt,</hi> which duty is required of <hi>Catholike People,</hi> but only once in the yeare, but performed by them with great comfort and edification, very of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten; ſo that a man may ſee and wonder to ſee many hundreds at one Altar to communicate every <hi>Sunday</hi> with great devotion, and likely no day paſſe, but divers do confeſſe, are abſolved, and receive the <hi>bleſſed Sacrament.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The poor <hi>Commons</hi> of <hi>England</hi> are freed from this comfort; neither is it poſſible, (unleſſe their
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:97574:45"/> 
                     <hi>Miniſters</hi> had the ſeat of Secrecie) for them to uſe it. And what is the liberty that they have inſtead thereof? Surely the <hi>ſervants</hi> have great liberty a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt their <hi>Maſters</hi> by this meanes, the <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> againſt their <hi>Parents,</hi> the <hi>People</hi> againſt their <hi>Prelates,</hi> the <hi>Subjects</hi> againſt their <hi>King,</hi> and all againſt the <hi>Church of Chriſt,</hi> that is againſt their own good, and the Common ſalvation; for without the uſe of this <hi>Sacrament,</hi> neither can Inferiors be kept in awe, but by the <hi>Gallowes,</hi> which will not ſave them from hell; nor Superiors be ever told of their Errors, but by <hi>Rebellion,</hi> which will not bring them to heaven. Theſe &amp; ſuch like be the liberties, that both Prince &amp; People do enjoy by the want of <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> and of <hi>Catholike Religion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>43. As for the liberty of making Lawes in Church-matters, the <hi>Common Lawyer</hi> may perhaps make an advantage of it, and therefore greatly ſtand upon it, but to the common people it is no pleaſure at all, but rather a great burthen. For the great Multitude of <hi>Statutes,</hi> which have been made ſince the <hi>Schiſme,</hi> (which are five times more then ever they were before, ſince the name of <hi>Parliament</hi> was in <hi>England)</hi> hath cauſed alſo an infinite num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of <hi>Lawyers,</hi> all which muſt live by the <hi>Commons,</hi> and raiſe new Families, which cannot be done without the decay of the old. And if the <hi>Canons</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> and the <hi>Courts of Confeſſion</hi> were in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſt, the <hi>Lawyers</hi> market would ſoon be marred.</p>
                  <p>And therefore moſt of your Lawyers in this point are <hi>Puritans,</hi> &amp; do ſtill furniſh the <hi>Parliament,</hi> with grievances againſt the <hi>Clergie,</hi> as knowing very well, that their own glory came at the firſt from the <hi>Court Infidell,</hi> and therefore cannot ſtand with the Authority of the <hi>Church,</hi> which came at the firſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:97574:45"/> from the <hi>Court Chriſtian.</hi> I ſpeak not againſt the Ancient Lawes of <hi>England,</hi> which ſince <hi>King Ethelberts</hi> time were all <hi>Catholike,</hi> nor againſt the honeſt Lawyers of <hi>England.</hi> I know many, and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nour all good men among them, and do hope for better times by the learning wiſedom, &amp; moderation of the chiefeſt. But I am verily perſwaded that the pretended liberties of the Commons, to make Lawes in matter of Religion, doth burthen the Common wealth, and both prejudice <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and pleaſure none at all, but the <hi>Puritan,</hi> and pet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty-fogging Lawyer, that would faine fetch the an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiquity of his Common Law from the <hi>Saxons,</hi> that were before <hi>King Ethelbert.</hi> So that whether we reſpect the ſpirituall inſtruction and comfort, or the temporall wealth and liberty of the Commons of <hi>England,</hi> if the <hi>Puritan Preacher,</hi> and <hi>Puritan Lawyer,</hi> who both do ſeek the overthrow of the <hi>Church,</hi> and deceive, and conſume the people, would let them alone, there would quickly appeare no reaſon of their Sta<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e at all, why they ſhould hate the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> that is ſo comfortable, and beneficiall unto them, or maintain the <hi>Schiſme<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> that with ſugred ſpeeches, and counterfait faces doth ſo much abuſe them.</p>
                  <p>44. I am therefore in very aſſured hope, that by my coming to the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> beſides the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfying, and ſaving of my own ſoule, I ſhall do no ill ſervice to <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> neither in reſpect of your ſelfe, nor your Children, nor in reſpect of your <hi>Lords,</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> and that there is no reaſon concerning the State in any of theſe, that is ſufficient to diſſwade unity. There is only the
<note n="*" place="margin">The Proteſtant Clergie are now like to find this a true prediction.</note> 
                     <hi>Clergy</hi> left
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:97574:46"/> which (if <hi>Calviniſme</hi> may go on, and prevaile as it doth) ſhall not in the next age be left to be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied.</p>
                  <p>And there is little reaſon, that any man that loves the <hi>Clergie,</hi> ſhould deſire to ſatisfie ſuch <hi>Cler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gie</hi> men, as do under hand favour <hi>Calviniſts,</hi> and maintain ſuch points of Doctrine, as if <hi>your Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties</hi> favour were not, would out of hand overthrow the <hi>Clergie,</hi> and inſtead of them ſet up a few <hi>ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendary Preachers,</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>45. There never was, is, or ſhall be any well ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led State in the world, either Chriſtian, or Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, but the <hi>Clergie</hi> or <hi>Prieſthood</hi> was, is, and muſt be a principall part of the Government de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pending upon none, but him only, whom they ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe to be their God. But where <hi>Calviniſme</hi> pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailes, three or four ſtipendary <hi>Miniſters,</hi> that muſt preach, as it ſhall pleaſe <hi>Mr. Mayor,</hi> and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, may ſerve for a whole City. And indeed if their opinions be true, it is but a folly for any State <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>o maintain any more. For if God hath prediſtina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted a certain Number to be ſaved, without any con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition at all of their being in the viſible <hi>Church</hi> by Faith, or their perſevering therein by good works; If God hath reprobated the greateſt part of the world, without any reſpect at all of their infidelity, hereſie, or wicked life; If the Faith of <hi>Chriſt</hi> be nothing els, but the aſſured perſwaſion of a Mans own Predeſtination to glory, by him; If the <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> be nothing but ſignes, and badges of that grace, which a man hath before by the <hi>carnall Covenant</hi> of his Parents faith; If <hi>Prieſthood</hi> can do nothing but preach the Word (as they call it) which Lay-men muſt judge of and may preach too, if they will, where occaſion ſerves;
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:97574:46"/> If the ſtudie an I knowledge of Antiquity, Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſality, and Conſent be not neceſſary, but every man may expound <hi>Scripture,</hi> as his own ſpirit ſhall move him; If I ſay, theſe and ſuch like opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions be as true, as they are among <hi>Calviniſts</hi> in the world common, and in <hi>England</hi> too much fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured, and maintained, there will certainly appear no reaſon at all to your <hi>Parliament,</hi> whenſoever <hi>your Majeſty</hi> or your Succeſſor ſhall pleaſe to ask them, why they ſhould be at ſo great a charge as they are, to maintain ſo needleſſe a party, as theſe opinions do make the <hi>Clergy</hi> to be. They can have a great many more <note place="margin">How right this points upon the Doctrine of theſe times.</note> Sermons, a great deale better cheap, and in the opinion of <hi>Calviniſme,</hi> the Clergy do no other ſervice. They that do in England favour, and maintain thoſe opinions, and ſuppreſſe, and diſgrace thoſe that do confute them; they, although themſelves can be content to be <hi>Lords,</hi> and go in <hi>Rochets,</hi> are indeed the greateſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies of the <hi>Clergy.</hi> And it were no great matter for the <hi>Clergy</hi> they might eaſily turn Lay, and live as well as they do for the moſt part. But it is a thing full of compaſſion, and commiſeration to ſee, that by theſe falſe and wicked opinions, the <hi>Divell,</hi> the the Father of theſe and all other lies, doth daily take poſſeſſion of the ſoules of your Subjects, both of <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe kind of Clergy men I confeſſe, I do not deſire to ſatisfie any other way, then as I have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies done, that is by the moſt friendly and plain confutation of their errors, to ſhew them the truth. As for other Clergy men that are conformable to the <hi>Religion</hi> eſtabliſhed by Law, as well for their
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:97574:47"/> Doctrine, as for their Diſcipline, if they be good Schollers, and temperate men, (as I know many of them are) they cannot but in their judgements approve the truth of <hi>Catholike Religion;</hi> and if it were not for fear of loſſe, or diſgrace to their wives, and Children, they would be as glad as my ſelfe, that a more temperate courſe might be held, and more liberty afforded unto <hi>Catholikes,</hi> and <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Religion</hi> in <hi>England.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Theſe <hi>Clergy-men,</hi> I am, and ever ſhall be deſirous to ſatisfie, not only in reſpect of themſelves, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo in reſpect of their wives and children, whom I am ſo far from condemning and diſliking, as that I do account my ſelfe one of them, and I deſire no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more in this world, then in the toleration of <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> to live &amp; die among them. And therefore I have had ſo great care in this point, as before I did ſubmit my ſelf to the <hi>Catholike Church,</hi> I received aſſurance from ſome of the greateſt, that if <hi>your Majeſty</hi> would admit the Ancient ſubordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the <hi>Church of Canterbury</hi> unto that <hi>Mother Church</hi> by whoſe authority all other <hi>Churches in England</hi> at the firſt were, and ſtill are ſubordinate unto <hi>Canterbury,</hi> and the free uſe of that <hi>Sacra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> for which eſpecially all the Churches in Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendome were firſt founded; the Pope for his part would confirme the <hi>Intereſt</hi> of all thoſe, that have preſent poſſeſſion in any Eccleſiaſticall living in <hi>England;</hi> And would alſo permit the free uſe of the <hi>Common Prayer Book</hi> in Engliſh for Morning and Evening Prayer, with very little or no alteration, And for the contentment and ſecurity of <hi>your Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty,</hi> he would give you not only any ſatisfaction but all the honor, that with the unity of the <hi>Church,</hi> and the ſafety of <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> may be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired;
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:97574:47"/> which ſeemed to me ſo reaſonable, as being before ſatisfied of the truth of <hi>Catholike Religion,</hi> I could ask no more. So that I am verely perſwaded, that by yeilding to that truth, which I could not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, I have neither neglected my duty, and ſervice to <hi>your Majeſty,</hi> and your Children, nor my reſpect and honor to your <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons,</hi> nor my love and kindneſſe to my honeſt friends, and bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren of the Clergy; but rather that my Example and my Prayers ſhall do good unto all.</p>
                  <p>47. But that which I muſt truſt to, when all the reſt will faile me, is the ſervice of God, and ſaving of my ſoule in the unity of that <hi>Church,</hi> which was founded by <hi>Chriſt</hi> himſelfe, and ſhall continue un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>till his coming againe, wherein all the <hi>Saints</hi> of God have ſerved him on earth, and do enjoy him in heaven, without which <hi>Holy Catholike Church,</hi> there is no <hi>Communion of Saints,</hi> no <hi>forgiveneſſe of ſinnes,</hi> no hope of <hi>Reſurection unto life ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſting.</hi> I beſeech <hi>your Majeſty</hi> let not <hi>Calvins Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Praedeſtinatorum</hi> deceive you, it may ſerve a <hi>Turk,</hi> as well as a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> it hath no faith but opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, no hope, but preſumption, no <hi>Charity,</hi> but luſt, no faith, but a fancie, no God, but an Idoll. For <hi>Deus eſt omnibus Religionibus commune Nomen,</hi> All Religions in the world, begin their <hi>Creed,</hi> with I <hi>believe in God.</hi> But <hi>homini extra Eccleſiant, Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligio ſua eſt cultus phantaſmatum ſuorum;</hi> and <hi>er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ror ſuus eſt Deus ſuus,</hi> as <hi>S. Auguſtine</hi> affirmeth, <hi>Epist.</hi> 64.</p>
                  <p>48. I have more things to write, but the haſt of anſwering <hi>your Majeſties</hi> Commandement, ſignifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to me by <hi>Sir Thomas Lake</hi> his Letters, hath made me commit many faults in writing this very ſuddenly, for which I crave pardon, and cut off the reſt.</p>
                  <pb n="54" facs="tcp:97574:48"/>
                  <p> But for my returning into <hi>England,</hi> I can an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer no otherwiſe but thus, I have ſent you my ſoule in this <hi>Treatiſe,</hi> and if it may find entertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and paſſage, my body ſhall moſt gladly fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low after. And if not, I pray God I ſend my ſoule to heaven, and my body to the grave, aſſoon as may be. In the mean time, <hi>I will rejoyce in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but only in the Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> which is the glory of your <hi>Crown.</hi> And therefore I will triumph therein, not as being gone from you to your adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſary, but as being gone before you to your <hi>Mother,</hi> where I deſire, and hope for ever to continue</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Your Majesties true Servant, and Beadſman, <hi>B. CARIER.</hi>
                     </signed>
                     <dateline>
                        <hi>Liege</hi>
                        <date>
                           <hi>Decemb.</hi> 12. <hi>Anno,</hi> 1613.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </closer>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <l>Multum incola fuit anima mea</l>
                        <l>Cum his qui oderunt pacem; eram pacificus,</l>
                        <l>Cum loqucbar illis, impuguabant me gratis.</l>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
